欢迎来到2013至2014秋季学期
Okay, well, welcome to Lecture number 8
斯坦福大学CS193P第八讲
of Stanford CS193P, fall of 2013 and 14,
今天我们先讲讲
and today, we are going to talk about
Objective-C的内容
a couple of "Objective-C" things first.
主要是语言特性
Language features, basically,
然后会讲一下动画
and then we're going to talk about animation.
动画是今天的主题
So animation is our topic of the day,
最后我会做一个示例
I'll be starting a demo at the end,
今天开始 周三完成
which we'll finish on Wednesday.
我会演示全部讲到的内容
And I'm going to demo pretty much everything I talk about,
包括Objective-C
including the Objective-C things,
甚至还包括
and even including some of the things
上周讲过的内容
we talked about last week,
所以会是一个大型且复杂的示例演示
so it's going to be a very big, comprehensive demo,
所以要分成两节课完成
that's why it runs over into two things.
首先是Objective-C的内容
So the first objective-C thing,
我们要讲的是协议
we're going to talk about is protocols.
我之前提到过
I hinted at this earlier in the quarter.
这个方法会让id更安全
This is a way that we're gonna make id a little more useful
让它更加有用
by making it a little safer, okay?
我们已经有了内省机制 可以让id更安全
And we already have introspection to make id safer.
如果我们有一个id
When we have something that's an id,
我们知道它是一个指向某个对象的指针
we know it's a pointer to some object,
我们不知道对象的类型
we don't know what kind of object,
我们知道如何在运行时用内省来询问
we know how to use introspection to ask at runtime,
你是什么类型的对象呢
"What kind of object are you?"
你响应哪种方法呢
"What kind of methods do you respond to?"
这样不错 但是下面这样更好
That's nice, but it would be better if,
如果我们可以在代码中增加说明
in our code, we could document in a way
让代码阅读者和编译器
that both the reader of our code can understand
都可以理解
and also that the compiler can understand
我们想用那个id做什么
what it is we intend, okay, with that id.
我们打算对那个id调用哪个方法
What methods we plan to call on that id.
这就是protocol协议的功能
And so that's what protocols do.
基本上就是语法
It's basically syntax,
只是编译器中的语法
it's just syntax in the compiler,
仅此而已
nothing more than that.
与NSString *和id一样
It's kind of the same thing in NSString star versus id,
只是编译器中语法的不同
that's really just syntax in the compiler,
在运行时并没有区别
it makes no difference at runtime.
语法的基本部分是这样的
And the fundamental part of the syntax is right here,
id <Protocol> obj
id angle bracket protocol obj.
声明了一个obj变量
So that's declaring a variable of type "obj"
它是一个id
which is an id,
但是加上了协议部分
but it's got this additional little thing, my protocol,
可以告诉编译器和阅读者
which tells the compiler and readers
更多代码的信息
of your code a little bit more.
我们来讲一下协议和它的工作原理
So let's talk about protocols and how this all works.
首先 我们要讲的是
The first thing we're going to talk about
如何声明一个协议
is how to declare a protocol.
声明协议的方法
And declaring a protocol looks almost exactly the same
和@interface声明几乎完全一样
as an at sign interface statement.
我们在@interface中放的是
At sign interface is where you put
所有公有的方法和属性
all your methods and properties that are public,
或者可以在实现文件顶部
or you can have an at sign interface
添加一个@interface
at the top of your implementation
来放私有的方法和属性
and have private methods and protocols-- properties.
协议也是一样的
And the same thing for protocol, just you say
只不过把@interface换成了@protocol
at sign protocol instead of at sign interface.
协议只是方法的声明
Now, a protocol is just a declaration of the methods.
没有实现部分
There's no implementation,
所以@protocol没有对应的@implementation
so there's no at sign implementation for an at sign protocol.
我们说的只是方法
We're just talking about the methods.
协议中的方法默认是必须实现的
And the methods in a protocol by default are all required, okay,
因此如果有人
so that means if someone wants to say
要实现这个协议
that they implement this protocol,
必须实现全部这些方法
they have to implement all these methods,
这些是这个示例协议中
and so those are all the methods
所有的方法
in my little sample protocol here.
你可以在这里加一个@optional
You can make some of them optional
将一部分方法变为可选的
by putting at sign optional in there.
现在 下面这些方法都是可选的了
And now, all the rest of those are optional,
在现在这个示例中 someMethod是必需的
so now in this example, someMethod is required,
下面其他的都是可选的
but all the rest are optional.
你还可以再加一个@required
And you can put at sign required,
在下面这里
again, down a little lower.
现在就只有methodWithArgument是可选的
Now, all of these are required
其余都是必需的
except for methodWithArgument is optional.
所以基本上 我们是定义了一堆方法
So, we're basically defining a little pile of methods,
其中有些是必需的
some of which are required,
有些是可选的
and some of which are optional, okay,
协议声明就是这样的
that's what a protocol declaration is all about.
我在@protocol Foo后面加了个<Xyzzy>
Now you see how I've added Xyzzy and angle brackets
看到了吗
after protocol Foo there?
它的意思是
So what that says is, if you want to implement,
如果你想要实现协议Foo
if you want to say you implement protocol Foo,
就也要实现Xyzzy协议中全部必需的方法
you also have to implement all the required methods of protocol Xyzzy.
不管是什么方法
Whatever that is.
大体上有点像是父协议
Okay? So it's basically a way of kind of like super protocol,
不是继承之类的
it's not really like inherent or anything,
就是增加了协议
but just kind of adds to the methods
必须要实现的方法
that is required by a protocol,
实际上 这里可以添加多个协议
and in fact, you can have multiple ones,
现在这个协议要求你实现
so here's protocols now requiring you implement
Xyzzy协议和NSObject协议
the Xyzzy protocol and a protocol called NSObject.
现在我们来说一下这个NSObject协议
Okay, now, let's talk about this NSObject protocol
因为它是一个很常见的协议
because it's a very common protocol.
大家都很熟悉NSObject类 对吧
You're used to the NSObject class, right?
NSObject协议基本上就是一个
And NSObject protocol is basically a protocol
包括了NSObject类中全部方法的协议
that includes almost all the methods in the NSObject class.
为什么要这样做呢
Okay. And why do we do this?
为什么要同时创建一个叫做NSObject的协议
Why do we have a protocol named NSObject
和一个叫NSObject的类呢
and a class named NSObject,
二者几乎有完全相同的方法
and they have pretty much the same methods in it,
isEqual isKindOfClass description performSelector
isEqual, isKindOfClass, description, performSelector,
全部这些NSObject的内容
all those NSObject things.
是因为有时我们在声明协议时
The answer is because we sometimes want to declare a protocol
有些方法是必需的
where some methods are required,
但我们还想让实现这个协议的对象
but we also want to require the thing
从本质上说 是一个NSObject
that implements the protocol to essentially be an NSObject.
我们希望它是一个NSObject
Okay. We want it to be an NSObject,
我们也许想要用内省等等
we want to be able to maybe use introspection, things like that.
唯一的方法就是让这个协议
Well, the only way to do that is to have the protocol
有一个父协议 附加的协议
have like a super protocol, you know, an additional protocol,
所以我们直接将NSObject中全部的方法
and so we just took all the methods in NSObject,
放到一个大协议中
we put them all in a big protocol
然后让NSobject来实现那个协议
and have NSObject implement that protocol.
所以NSObject协议和类
Okay. So NSObject protocol and class,
差不多有完全一样的方法
all the same methods pretty much.
只不过NSObject类
Okay. It's just that NSObject class
真正实现了这些方法
is an actual implementation of those methods.
那么这些协议声明...
So where do these protocol declaration--
抱歉 有问题吗
Oh yeah, sorry, question?
在Java中 所有类都是自动从对象继承的
In Java, all class is automatically inherit from object,
NSObject不是这样吗
is that not the case with NSObject here?
问题是 在Java中
Yeah, so the question is, in Java,
差不多所有的类都是从对象继承的
all class is pretty much inherit from object,
Objective-C中不是这样的
and that's not true in Objective-C,
你可以直接用
you could have a class where it just says
@interface 类名 没有冒号和父类
at sign interface, name of class, no colon super class.
这种情况下 它不会继承任何方法
In which case, it inherits no methods from anywhere.
只会有它自己的方法
Okay, will only have its own method.
但我们不会这样做
We never do that, however.
在iOS中 我们总是从NSObject继承而来
In iOS we always inherit from NSObject.
因为我们需要内省等这些方法
Because we want the introspection and all these things,
但这是惯例
but it's by convention rather than
而不是编译器的强制要求
by some sort of enforcement for the compiler.
那么 这些方法的@protocol声明
Alright, so these at sign protocol declarations
要放在哪里呢
of these methods, where do they go?
放在头文件中
They go in header files,
可以放在它们自己的头文件中
they can go in their own header file,
比如Foo协议的头文件就是Foo.h
so like have a Foo.h for my protocol Foo,
或者可以放在某个相关类的头文件中
or they can go in the header file of some related class,
比如要实现那个协议的某个类
like some class that wants somebody to implement that protocol,
也可以放在它的头文件中
you could put it in there.
比如iOS中有滚动视图类
So, for example, iOS has scroll view class, right?
用于滚动
For scrolling.
我们下周会讲到它
We're going to talk about that next week.
它有一个协议叫做UIScrollViewDelegate
It has a protocol called the UIScrollViewDelegate,
里面有一堆willScroll didScroll等这类方法
which is a bunch of willScroll, didScroll things, methods,
这个协议只适用于UIScrollView
and it's only good for UIScrollView, so that delegate,
所以这个协议是在UIScrollView.h中定义的
that protocol is defined in UIScrollView.h,
而不是在它自己的头文件中
not in its own header file.
所以这两种方法大家可以任选
Okay? So you can kind of do which ever one you want,
两种方法都会见到
and you'll see them both ways.
现在我们声明了协议
Alright, so now we have the protocol declared,
定义了这些方法
we defined this little bundle of methods,
也许包括属性的setter和getter
including the setters and getters of properties, perhaps,
现在要有一个类保证实现这个协议
now some class has to promise to implement that protocol.
如果你是一个类
And how do you promise
如何保证实现一个协议呢
to implement a protocol if you're a class?
只要在@interface那一行
You just put angle brackets, the name of the protocol,
加上<协议名>
on your at sign interface line.
这一行是我的公有的@interface
Okay? So here, it's my public at sign interface line,
myClass 从NSobject继承来的 然后是<Foo>
myClass, inherits from NSObject, angle brackets Foo.
这表示的是
That means my class is promising
我的类向编译器和阅读者们保证
to the compiler and to readers of this code,
我要实现Foo中全部必须实现的方法
I'm going to implement all the required methods in Foo.
我做出了这样的保证
Okay? So I'm just making that promise.
可以像这样公开保证
And you can make the promise publicly like that,
或者也可以将其变为私有的
or you can make the promise privately
方法是将其放在@interface myClass()中
by putting it in your at sign interface myClass() thing
这是在实现部分中的
that goes in your implementation,
需要的话 可以直接放在那里
you can just put it there if you want.
只用于需要实现...
That's if you only need to be able to implement that--
你只需要为实现文件中独有的某对象
you're only required to implement that protocol
实现那个协议
for something that's in your implementation only, okay,
不是公有的
not on your public thing.
现在我有了一个协议
Okay, so now I've got a protocol,
有了一个对象
I've got an object,
至少有一个说了要实现它 然后呢
at least one that signs up to implement it, now what?
现在我可以声明id类型的变量
Well, now I can declare variables that are ids
加上附加要求
with the additional requirement
要求实现某个协议中的必需方法
to implement the required methods of a protocol.
也就是id <Foo> obj
So id angle bracket Foo obj,
希望大家现在明白它的意思了
hopefully, you understand what that means now,
它表示obj是一个变量 是一个id类型
that means obj is a variable, it's an id,
我不知道它的类是什么 它是个id
I have no idea what class it is, okay, it's id,
是完全不可知的
it's completely blind,
但是我知道它实现了
however, I know it implements
Foo中全部私有或必需的方法
all the private or the required methods in Foo. Okay?
它也许也实现了某些可选方法
And it might implement some of the optional ones too,
但我知道至少它实现了必需的方法
but I know at least the required ones.
如果我用id <Foo> obj=[[MyClass alloc] init]
So if I say id <Foo> obj MyClass alloc init,
这样就很不错 因为在上一张幻灯片中
that looks good because on the previous slide
我说了MyClass保证会实现Foo
I just said that MyClass promised to implement Foo.
编译器会很喜欢这行代码
So the compiler is going to love that.
但如果用的是id <Foo> obj=[NSArray array]
But if I said id Foo obj NS equals NSArray,
编译器不喜欢这样的
that compiler is not going to like that
因为array显然没有实现协议Foo
because array clearly don't implement a protocol Foo.
它们没有实现那些方法
They don't implement those methods.
所以如果这样用了 编译器会警告你
Okay? So the compiler will warn you in that case.
你这样做的话 编译器会发出警告
Okay, so the compiler here will warn you if you do this,
如果你说了要实现一个协议
it will also warn you if you sign up to do a protocol,
保证了要做某些事情
you promise to do something,
但你却没有实现必需的方法
and you don't implement the methods that are required,
编译器也会发出警告
it will warn you about that too,
所以两种问题都会发出警告
okay so it will warn you both coming and going.
除了声明变量
In addition to declaring variables,
比如例子中的局部变量之外
like local variables under the examples there,
你还可以传递它们
you can also pass these around,
将这些带有协议的id
these ids that are modified by the protocol,
作为方法的参数
as arguments to methods.
还可以作为属性
And as properties.
它就是另外一种类型
Okay? So, it's really just another type,
不像NSString*那样
it's not quite an NSString star
你知道它的类是什么
where you know exactly the class
知道全部方法的功能
and all the methods exactly that it does,
但也不是像id那样
but it's not quite an id,
完全什么都不知道
where you know nothing about it.
它在二者之间
It's in between.
它是一个id
Right? It's an id,
但你知道Foo中的某些方法
but you kind of know some of the methods in Foo.
类似于静态类型
Just like static typing,
只是编译器中的语法糖
this is all just syntactic sugar in the compiler,
运行时毫无区别
makes absolutely no difference at runtime,
编译器生成的代码
no code is generated any differently
不会因为它们发生任何变化
by the compiler because of these things.
只不过编译器现在可以发出警告了
The compiler is just able to warn you now.
只有这点区别
That is the only difference.
有些人不太理解
Some people had a little difficulty accepting this,
但就是这样的
but it's true.
编译器生成的代码不会因为这些协议
No code generation is any different by the compiler
发生任何变化
because of these protocols.
与NSString和id一样
Same thing with NSString star versus id.
编译器生成的代码
It's all exactly the same stuff
是完全一样的
gets generated by the compiler.
只不过编译器可以发出警告
It's just the compiler can warn you
因为它们知道你要做什么
because they know what you intend.
iOS中 协议主要用于
Okay? The number-one use of protocols in iOS
委托和数据源
is delegation and data sources.
这就回到了
This is back to--
还记得第一节课讲MVC的时候吗
Remember lecture 1, I had the MVC
我说视图可以向它们的控制器发送消息
and I told you that the views could talk to their controller
方法是通过不可视结构化通信
with blind structured communication,
我们讲了各种will方法
and we talked about will do this,
did方法 还有数据源
did do that, or the data source,
dataAt和count等等
which is data at, count, that kind of stuff.
还记得这些内容吗 这种通信方式
All of those, remember that communication?
我们就是这样实现的
This is how we do that.
通信是不可视的 因为它们是id类型
So it's blind, because they're ids,
视图通信时使用的是id类型
the views are talking through ids.
但它是结构化的 因为视图向其他不可视对象发送消息时
But it's structured because there's a protocol
使用的是一个协议
that the view uses to talk to that object blindly,
所以它知道里面的内容
so it knows what's in there.
比如说 我们来讲一下
So let's talk about, for example,
视图的数据源协议
the dataSource protocols of views.
如果是一个表视图
If it was a table view, let's say,
表视图是一个通用视图
a table view is a generic view
用来展示信息表
for showing a table of information,
它用来获取数据源的协议是
its protocol for accessing its data source
表中有多少行
is how many rows are there,
现在给我第七行的数据
and now give me the data at row 7,
给我第500行的数据
give me the data at row 500.
这就是它的协议
Okay? That's its protocol.
这些方法
Those methods.
count和dataAt 还有其他方法
Count, and data at, it has other ones,
但这些是最基础的方法
but those are the basic ones, okay?
我们真的很需要这些数据源协议
And we really need those data source protocols
因为视图不能自己保存数据
because views can't own their data.
表视图不能抓取全部数据 然后显示出来
That table view can't grab all its data and display it,
它需要不断地询问其他对象
it has to keep asking someone else,
但它并不想绑定某个数据源
but it doesn't want to be tied to any source of the data,
所以它最好是一个id 是不可见的
so it wants to be an id, it wants to be blind.
我们下周讲到表视图时
Okay? And we'll see all this next week
会讲到这一部分
when we talk about table views.
除了不可视结构化通信之外
There are other uses of protocols
协议还可以用在其他地方
besides that blind structured communication,
我们今天会讲一个 也就是动画
and we're going to see one today which is animation,
我会讲得很清楚
and I'll let that speak for itself,
但是基本上 我们是要用
but basically we're going to have ids out there
具有动画性的id
that are animatable,
我们知道它们是具有动画性的
and we're going to know they're animatable
因为它们要实现某个特定协议
because they're going to implement a certain protocol,
我们就是通过这个方法知道
and that's how we're going to know
它们是具有动画性的
that they're animatable things,
UIView会实现这个协议
and UIView is going to implement that protocol
我们就是这样为视图添加动画的
and that's how we're going to animate our views.
我今天要讲的第二个objective-C知识点
Alright, the second objective-C thing
是block
I want to talk about today is blocks.
和协议完全不一样
Okay, it's a totally different thing that protocols.
block很重要 在iOS中广泛使用
Blocks very important, used throughout iOS,
实际上 讲到第五周或者第四周
in fact, sometimes I have difficulty getting
有的时候我很难不涉及到block
all the way to week 5 here or 4 without putting blocks
因为它在iOS的API中太常用了
because it's so much in the API of iOS.
什么是block
What is a block?
block就是一段代码块
A block is a block of code.
为什么我们要定义一个术语block
Okay? Why do we define this term block,
只是用来代表一段代码块 我们已经知道了
just to mean block of code, we already know that,
因为这段代码块
it's because it's a block of code
可以嵌入到其他代码中
that can be embedded inside other code,
可以作为参数进行传递 储存在数组中
passed as an argument, stored in an array, okay?
我们可以操纵这段代码块
So it's a block of code that we manipulate
在API中进行使用
and move around our API.
那么是什么样子的呢
So what does it look like?
这个示例是
Here's an example of a method
一个参数为block的方法
that takes a block as an argument.
这是在调用这个方法
Okay? This is the calling of this method.
这是一个NSDictionary方法 真正的方法
There's an NSDictionary method, it's a real method,
叫做enumerateKeysAndObjectsUsingBlock
it's called enumerateKeysAndObjectsUsingBlock.
参数是一个没有返回值的block
Okay? The argument is a block that has no return value
带有三个参数 其中前两个是id类型
and takes three arguments, two of the arguments are ids,
分别是字典中的键和值
which are they keys and values in the dictionary,
第三个参数是一个BOOL
and a third one is actually a BOOL star,
一个指向BOOL的指针
a pointer to a BOOL,
是一个外部的BOOL
it's an outgoing BOOL.
当调用这个方法时
Okay? And basically when you call this method,
字典会重复执行这段代码块
Dictionary will execute that block of code, repeatedly,
每对键值执行一遍
for every key and value,
直到你将*stop设为了YES
until you set the stop, star stop, to yes,
或者循环执行完全部键值
or until it runs out of keys and values.
而且它真的会实现
Okay? And it's actually going to implement
中间的代码
that code that's right there,
嵌套在方法调用中的代码
embedded inside that method call.
看到这个枚举键值方法的
You can see the open square bracket
左方括号了吗
for enumerate keys and objects,
在aDictionary前面
before aDictionary,
而右方括号在下面的大括号后面
the close square bracket is down after the curly brace.
真正的大括号表示的代码
Okay? So the code, the actual curly brace,
放在中间
we put right in there,
放在方法调用的中间
in the middle of our method call.
而在一般计算机科学的其他语言中
Other languages, in computer science in general,
我们把这叫做闭包
we call this a closure.
有多少人知道闭包这个词
Okay, how many people know the name closure,
以前听到过
ever heard that before?
好的 那大家就都知道这是什么了 是一个闭包
Okay, so you guys generally know what this is, it's a closure.
Objective-C中的block常以脱字符号^开始
Blocks in Objective-C always start with the caret.
它代表着block的开始
That's the magic block character.
然后可能会指定一个返回类型
And then there might be a return type, possibly specified,
可能会有一些参数
and maybe some arguments, possibly,
然后是一个大括号 一些代码
and then a curly brace, and some code,
最后以大括号结束
and an end curly brace.
当然 还有一些有趣的功能
Now, of course, to make this really interesting,
比如编译器知道如何使用一个局部变量
the compiler knows how to do things like have local variables
在block使用之前声明
that are declared before the block is used,
在block内部使用
work inside the block.
如果我用了这个block
Okay? So if I had that block
我希望不只在发现ENOUGH键时停下来
and I wanted to stop not just when I see the key ENOUGH
还要在发现stopValue这个值时也停下来
but also when I see the value, stopValue,
它是一个局部变量
which is a local variable defined in the scope
是在调用enumerateKeysAndObjectsUsingBlock时定义的
that's calling the method enumerateKeysAndObjectsUsingBlock,
我可以用它
I can use it.
编译器确保了可以将它的值
The compiler makes sure that the value of that
正确地传递进来
gets properly passed in.
你有问题吗
However-- you have a question?
这个是静态范围吗
Now is this statically scoped for using things outside?
对 这是...
Uh...yeah, it is the loc--
aDictionary enumerateKeysAndObjects的调用范围
whatever scope the aDictionary enumerateKeysAndObjects,
不管它的范围是什么
that call, whatever scope there,
它的范围就是变量的使用范围
that's the scope in which the variables can be used,
基本上就是局部堆栈
which is pretty much the local stack, right?
你自己的堆栈
The stack from your thing,
但是这些变量是只读的
now, those variables though are read only.
如果再增加一个BOOL类型stoppedEarly
Okay? So if I had another one, a BOOL stoppedEarly
然后我想在block内部设置它
and I tried to set that inside my block,
就会出现错误
that would be an error,
编译器不允许这样的操作
compiler would not allow that, okay?
因为stoppedEarly是只读的
Because stoppedEarly is read only.
但是其实有一种方法
However, there's actually a way to make it
能够让变量不是只读的
so it's not read only,
方法是在变量前面加上__block
which is to put underbar, underbar, block in front of it.
如果你在局部变量前面
If you put underbar, underbar, block
加上双下划线block
in front of a local variable,
编译器就会生成一段代码
then the compiler will generate code
将stoppedEarly从栈中移到堆中
that transfers stoppedEarly off the stack into the heap
这样它就可以在block中使用了
so that it can be used by the block,
然后block结束时
and then when the block is finished,
它会将信息复制回堆中
it will copy the information back into the heap
再放回到栈上
and then back onto the stack.
都神奇地自动实现了
Okay? All happens magically.
所以如果你加上__block
So if you have underbar, underbar, block,
系统就知道怎样做了
it knows to do that.
只要加上这个神奇的__block
So that's the magic you put in there,
你的变量就可以读写了
and now your variables can go both ways,
这时stoppedEarly=YES就是合法的了
and now stoppedEarly is yes is legal.
如果变量是个实例变量
Okay? This also works
也是可以的
if the variable is an instance variable.
除了用setter和getter
We don't really access instance variables
我们并不直接获取实例变量
except for setters and getters,
那是因为实例变量
but that's because instance variables,
当然是在堆中的
of course, are in the heap.
因为全部对象都保存在堆中
Because all objects are stored in the heap.
那么block中使用的对象呢
What about objects that are messaged inside of a block?
因为这里有个特殊的问题需要考虑
Because there's a little special thing to think about there.
如果我有一个字符串stopKey 值为ENOUGH
So if I had a string stopKey, which was enough,
我想在block中使用这个stopKey 就像这样
and I wanted to use stopKey inside that block, like this,
我要确保 也不是我要确保
I have to make sure-- well not I have to make sure,
编译器要确保它生成了代码
the compiler has to make sure that it generates code
运行环境要确保它正常工作
and the runtime has to make sure it works,
所以有一个强指针指向这个stopKey
so that stopKey, that there's a strong pointer to it,
否则执行这个block时
otherwise it could leave the heap
stopKey可能已经离开堆了
by the time this block executes.
因为这个block可以在任意时间执行
Because this block could execute at any time.
当你调用这个block时
Okay? This block happens to execute immediately
它会立刻执行
when you call this,
但是可以使用字典
but it's legal for the dictionary
抓取这个block 保存在某个地方
to grab this block and store it somewhere
在后面某个需要的时候再调用
and execute it sometime later that it wants to.
仔细听下面这点
Okay? So every time you-- listen to this carefully,
每次向block中的对象发送消息时
every time you send a message to an object inside a block,
系统就会创建一个指向该对象的强指针
a strong pointer is created to that object,
该指针会一直保持到block超出范围以后
and it stays around until the block goes out of scope,
直到block不存在
until the block no longer exists.
只要block存在
Okay? As long as that block exists,
消息中每个对象
a strong pointer to every single object
都会被一个强指针指着
in there this message will exist.
在仔细讲解之前 我想先讲个简写方法
Before I talk about that, I want to talk about some shorthand.
如果block没有参数 就像这个block一样
If the block has no arguments, like this block, see?
这里没有参数
No arguments there.
可以不用添加括号
You do not need to put the parentheses, okay?
直接删掉就行
You can just leave those off.
同样的 如果block的返回值...
And similarly, if the return value of the block--
这个block是大家第一次见到
so this block which is the first time
带有返回值的block
you've seen a block with a return value,
返回一个BOOL值 看到那个BOOL了吗
it returns a BOOL, see that BOOL?
如果返回值
If the return value can be inferred
能够从block的内容推断出来
from the contents of the block, right?
这个例子中 return [obj isKindOfClass: UIView class]
So in this case, return obj isKindOfClass UI class,
肯定会返回一个BOOL值
definitely going to return a BOOL,
不需要在这里再加一个BOOL
you do not need to put the BOOL there.
换句话说 如果能够推断出来
In other words, if it can be inferred,
系统就会自动为你识别出来
it will figure it out for you, okay?
可以直接省略一部分语法
So just to clean up the syntax,
不用总是再在那里加上BOOL等等
you don't have to put the BOOL in there all the time or whatever.
好了 接下来呢
Okay. Now.
我们来讲一下block是如何表现得像对象的
Let's talk about how blocks sort of act like objects.
block不是对象
Blocks are not objects, okay they're not,
但它们有时会表现得像对象
but they sort of act like objects
只表现在这一个小的方面
in the only in this fine really small way,
也就是它们可以被存储
which is, they can be stored.
自动引用计数会统计
Okay? And they are reference counted
它们的引用数目
by the automatic reference counter. Okay?
能够存储意味着它们可以被保存在变量中
So storing them means they can be stored in variables,
属性中 字典和数组中
in properties, and in dictionaries and arrays.
所以block可以像对象一样进行存储
Okay? So they can be stored just like they're objects,
但并不像对象那样可以理解消息
but they don't understand any messages like an object.
实际上 它们理解一个消息 就是复制
Actually, they understand one message which is copy,
这是一个挺重要的消息
which is kind of an important message
因为它会在堆中复制block
because that copies them in the heap,
如果你想要用一个指针始终指向block
and if you want to keep a pointer to a block around,
可能你要对它进行复制
you probably want to copy it, okay,
这样它才不会从栈中释放
so it doesn't just go off the stack somewhere.
比如说 这里我将一个block放入一个数组
So for example, here I am putting a block into an array,
我的类中有一个属性myBlocks
so I have a property in my class myBlocks,
是一个block的可变数组
it's a mutable array of blocks,
只要用self.myBlocks addObject:block
and I just say self dot myBlocks addObject colon a block.
我知道这看起来很奇怪 是很怪
Okay? I know this looks weird, and it is weird,
因为block不是对象
because blocks are not objects,
但当要将它们进行存储时
but they act like objects
和对象的操作是类似的
for this purpose of storing them in things.
非常好用
Okay? So pretty neat.
对了 我还没讲
And by the way, I have not talked about
如何调用block
basically how you would call this block.
如果我将这个block从数组中取出
Like if I grab this block out of this array
想要调用它 要怎么做呢
and wanted to invoke it, how would I do it?
我今天不讲
I'm not going to talk about that today,
但是会演示
but I'm going to show you
这样大家就能看到是怎样做的了
so that you can see it.
在这门课中 大家不需要实现调用
Really, you're not going to have to do that in this class,
因为要把block传递给iOS
because you're going to be passing blocks to iOS
它来执行它们
and it's going to be executing them,
但如果大家想知道 语法就是这样的
but if you wanted to know, that's the syntax,
有点像C函数语法
it's kind of like C-function syntax,
大家可以课下再看
you can look offline,
很可惜 我没有时间讲这个了
I just don't have time to cover it unfortunately.
这里有一个危险的地方
But there's a real danger lurking here.
在上面的这段代码中
Okay? In this code, above.
self doSomething这里
Okay, this self, doSomething, thing.
是什么
And what is it?
它叫做存储循环
Well, it's called a memory cycle.
有多少人知道存储循环是什么
How many people know what a memory cycle is?
不太多 很好 我来讲一下
Okay, not very many, that's good so I'll cover this.
出现存储循环问题的原因是
A memory cycle, it's caused
只要block存在
because all the objects inside that block
block中的所有对象
have a strong pointer to them,
就都有一个强指针指向它们
as long as the block exists.
比如在这段代码中
Okay? So, for example, in this code, self--
block会有一个强指针指向self
a strong pointer will be held by that block to self.
知道为什么吗
You see why?
因为只要这个block保存在数组中
Because the block, as long as it stays around in that array,
它就需要能够调用self doSomething
it needs to be able to call self doSomething,
所以它需要始终用一个强指针指向self
so it needs to always keep a strong pointer to self,
只要这个block存在
as long as the block exists.
但是问题是
However, the problem is
self也有一个强指针指向block
that self has a strong pointer to the block.
通过它的myBlocks数组 对吧
Through its myBlocks array. Right?
self有一个指向myBlocks的强指针
Self has a strong pointer to myBlocks,
myBlocks是一个数组
which is an array,
数组对其内容都是强引用的
the array always hold their things strongly,
现在它们都用强指针指向对方
so now both of them are pointing strongly to each other.
self指向block block指向self
The block is pointing to self, self is pointing to the block.
这种情况下 二者都无法从栈中释放
Neither of them can ever leave the heap in that situation
因为始终会有对方的强指针
because there's always going to be a strong pointer
指向自己
to them, each other's, right?
没有办法让一个先释放
One of them can't leave first
然后另外一个就没有指针指着了
and make it so there's no pointer to the other,
因为它们都不让对方释放
because they are keeping each other in.
这叫做存储循环
That's called a memory cycle.
我们得打破这种循环
Okay? And we have to break these cycles.
这是个严重的问题
Okay? This is a serious problem,
我们当然希望能够打破这种循环
you definitely want to be able to break these cycles,
方法是这样的
and here's how we do it.
我们要用一个局部变量
We're going to do it with a local variable.
局部变量都是怎样的
Okay? Now, local variables are all what?
都是强类型
They're all strong.
局部变量都是强类型
Right? Local variables are strong,
是指向堆中的强指针 指针变量
they're strong pointers into the heap, pointer variables,
直到方法结束 这时强指针被释放
until the method ends, and now the strong pointer goes away
这时局部变量
and so now that local variable obviously
显然就不再用强指针指向堆中的内容了
is not holding something in the heap by being strong.
但是有一种方法可以创建弱类型局部变量
But there is a way to actually create weak local variables,
就是在前面加上__weak
with underbar, underbar, weak.
将双下划线weak
Okay? Underbar, underbar, weak
添加到一个局部变量声明之前
before a local variable declaration
这个变量就是弱类型的了
will make that variable weak, okay?
记得吗 弱类型表示它不会在堆中保存该对象
Remember that weak means it's not keeping the object
如果没有其他元素指向它
in the heap, if no one else is pointing to it,
它就会被释放 弱变量变为nil
it just goes away, and the weak variable gets set to nil.
所以我要创建一个局部变量weakSelf
Okay? So I'm going to make a local variable, weakSelf,
它指向self 但用的是弱指针
which points to self, but is weak pointer to self,
现在我可以在block中使用它
and now I can use that inside this block that I added.
我要将doSomething发送给weakSelf
I'll send doSomething to weakSelf,
这时就不会再出现循环了
and now I don't have this cycle anymore,
因为block没有了指向self的强指针
because the block no longer has a strong pointer to self,
是一个弱指针
it has a weak pointer.
我们要使用这个方法
Okay? So yes, we will do this.
大家可能要在作业中用到
You might have to do it in your homework,
取决于你们的实现方法
depending on how you decide to implement it,
我肯定会在示例中演示它
and I will definitely do it in the demo today
大家可以看到是如何使用的
so you can see how this works. Okay?
我们使用自动引用计数时
This is really the only place we have these kind of cycles,
只会在这种情况下遇到这种循环
with ARC, with the automatic reference counter,
并不是太糟糕
it's not too bad,
但你要知道有这个问题 并处理它
you just have to know it's there, and deal with it.
好的
Okay.
在iOS中 何时使用block呢
So when do we use blocks in iOS?
可以用于枚举 我们刚才就用了字典
We use them for enumeration, you saw that dictionary,
枚举 键和值
enumerate, keys and values.
常用于枚举
We use it a lot for enumeration.
我们还会用于视图动画
We use it for view animation,
这节课后面的部分
I'm going to do the whole rest of this lecture
和下节课前面部分都是关于视图动画的
and the start of next lecture is going to be about that.
我们还会用于排序
And we use it for sorting.
你可以向数组发送消息 让这个数组进行排序
There's messages you can send to arrays like sort this array,
用这个block比较数组中的两个对象
and use this block to compare two objects in the array.
还用于通知
Okay? Notifications.
当进行广播时
Right? When a radio station broadcasts
不用发送通知消息
instead of sending a notification message,
可以直接说 执行这个block
you can say "Just execute this block"
当广播站进行广播时
when broadcast happens on the radio station.
错误处理程序很常见
Error handler is very common.
执行这个操作 出现错误时
Do this thing, and when an error happens,
执行这个block 我会进行处理
execute this block and I'll handle it.
完成处理程序同样很常见
Okay? Completion handlers also very common.
某个操作需要一段时间才能完成
Do this thing that's going to take a long time,
会在后台线程中完成
and it's gonna be done in a background thread,
当它完成时
and when it's done,
执行这个block 让我知道
execute this block to let me know.
实际上 动画会完成这个操作
Okay? Animation does that, in fact,
我们也会在动画中见到
we'll see that in animation too.
有问题吗
Question?
如果你在类中定义了一个方法
So you have like a method defined in your class
而你想将它作为block使用
and you want to use that function as a block.
有什么简单方法来引用它吗
Is there any easy way to refer to it,
还是必须要将它写成block呢
or do you have to like write it as a block?
问题是 如果我有一个方法
Yeah, so the question is, if I had a method,
定义在类中等等
defined in my class or whatever,
我想将它作为block的内容
and I want to use it as the contents of the block,
只要在block中调用self和那个方法
just call self and that method inside the block,
就可以调用了
and that will call it.
这个操作实际上很常用
That's a common thing to want to do, actually.
block还有一个非常非常重要的用处
A very, very important use of blocks,
我们会在后面的课程中讲到
which we're going to talk about later in the quarter,
就是多线程
is multi-threading.
就是让应用
Okay? Which is getting your application
同时执行多个操作
doing multiple things at the same time,
严格来说 不是同时
not really at the same time,
但看起来是同时执行
but seemingly at the same time.
我真的推荐大家...
And I really encourage you,
只有几个地方 我会让你们回去查看文档
this is one of the few times I'm going to tell you go look
这里就是其中之一 建议大家查看block相关文档
in the documentation to find out about blocks,
直接在Xcode文档中搜索block
just search for blocks in Xcode documentation,
就会找到相关内容
and you can find out things like
比如 如何声明一个block类型的局部变量
how to declare a local variable that is a block,
这类内容
and things like that,
因为我没有仔细讲这些内容
because I haven't really talked about those things.
我讲的关于block的内容
Mostly I've just talked to you enough about blocks
可以让大家学会调用参数为block的方法
to be able to call methods that take blocks as arguments.
到目前为止 我讲过的就是这些内容
Okay? That's all I've pretty much shown you so far.
这就是我想要讲的
Okay. So that's it for the Objective-C
Objective-C的内容
that I wanted to cover.
现在我们可以进入有趣的部分了 也就是动画
And now we can get into the fun stuff, which is animation.
今天这节课剩下的时间都是这个内容
Alright? So that's going to be the rest of today
周三可能还要再讲一会
and probably the start of Wednesday
因为这个示例很大
because this demo is really big.
iOS中有很多不同的动画
And there's lots of different animation that goes on in iOS.
我今天要讲的 大概只会在这门课上讲到
I'm going to talk today, and only really in this course,
是关于为视图添加动画的
for the most part, about animating views.
大家知道如何创建自定义视图 对吧
Okay? You know how to create custom views, right?
你甚至可以为非自定义视图添加动画
And you can even animate non-custom views,
按钮等等
buttons, or whatever you want,
就是要让视图在屏幕上移动
but basically making views move around the screen,
缩放 淡入淡出 旋转
get bigger and smaller, fade in and out, spin around and rotate,
这是我们要讲的内容
that's what we're going to talk about.
为视图添加动画
Okay? Animating views.
但还有其他动画
But there's other animation that goes on,
比如进入导航控制器后 进行点击
like when you go into a navigation controller, and you click,
一个新视图就会滑进来
and a new view slides in, okay?
这也是动画
That's animation. Alright?
如果是在地图应用中
And it's possible, also, okay you're in the maps app
在角落点击
and you click in the corner
它会卷起来 显示其他选项
and it curls up to show you other options?
这也是动画
That's animation, okay?
这种视图控制器的动画
All that kind of view controller animation,
我大概不会讲
I'm not going to talk about, for the most part.
但也有对这部分的支持
Okay? But that's all-- there's all support for that as well.
iOS中还有一套机制
There's also a whole other thing in iOS
叫做集合视图 是一个视图的集合
called the collection view, which is a collection of views
视图排列在网格中或是流程型
that kind of live in a grid, sort of, or in a flow,
这些都可以添加动画效果
kind of layout, and those all can be animated.
里面也有动画
What's going on in there as well,
但是我只会讲解视图的动画
okay, but I'm only going to talk about views.
它们的底层是这个Core Animation核心动画框架
Underneath all of that is this framework called core animation,
非常强大的框架
super powerful framework, I mean,
是技术等级的动画框架
industrial grade animation framework there,
但我们要通过比它高得多的层级入手
but we're going to be doing it all at a much higher level,
更容易编程
much easier to program, and you know, kind of easier to--
你不必知道太多
you don't have to know quite so much about the detail
动画工作的细节
of how animation really works.
Core Animation适用于那些专业动画人员
Whereas core animation is really for animation people
制作重要的动画效果
who want really to do serious animations,
很多iOS应用都是游戏之类的应用
and a lot of iOS applications are games, or other things
里面有很重要的动画
that have a very serious animation going on in there.
在iOS7中
By the way, in iOS 7
还有很多实现动画的工具
there's a lot of other things for doing animation,
比如 Sprite Kit用来添加sprite动画
for example, Sprite Kit is a way to animate sprites,
从本质上说是2D图形元素
which are essentially 2D graphic elements
以某种方式混合
that are being composited in a way
以此获得3D视觉环境
to try to get a 3D looking environment,
很多电子游戏就是这样的
like a lot of video games are,
我们甚至不会用到Sprite Kit
and we're not even going to touch Sprite Kit,
我认为不会的 除非最后一周用到了它
I don't think, unless we get to it the last week.
内容很多 我不可能全部讲到
So there's a lot of stuff that I can't possibly cover,
所以这里我们就只讲动画的基础部分
so let's just talk the basics here of animation.
为视图添加动画主要有三种方法
So there's three ways to animate views, basically.
第一种方法是
Okay? The first way is that
视图中有一些非常特殊的属性
there are some very special properties in view,
比如视图的frame属性
namely the view's frame,
记得吗 就是包含它的那个矩形
remember that's the rectangle enclosing it,
还有transform属性 讲卡牌游戏的时候
its transform, which we talked about briefly,
简单提到过
when we did the playing card thing,
transform指视图的缩放比例
transform is the view scale,
视图可以被放大缩小
can be used to scale it up and down,
以及旋转情况 视图可以被旋转
and it's rotation, views can be rotated,
还有移动距离
and also translation,
尽管通常情况下 我们会使用frame来移动
although usually for translation we use the frame,
直接移动frame
we move the frame around.
还有alpha 代表它的不透明度
And also alpha, its opacity,
可以在任意时间向视图中添加这三个的动画
these three things can be animated at any time into view.
意思是 你将它们设为新值
Meaning, you set them to a new value
它会立刻变为那个新值
and it will set to that new value immediately,
但是效果会过一段时间
but the effect will appear on screen animated
才以动画显示在屏幕上
over some amount of time.
我们来看一下它的工作原理
So, let's take a look at how this works.
是通过UIView的一个类方法实现的
It's done with a class method in UIView.
是UIView的类方法 而不是实例方法
Okay? A class method, it's not an instance method in UIView,
是一个类方法
it's a class method,
类方法的参数为动画参数
and the class method basically takes the animation parameters,
时间多长之类的
how long to take and stuff like that,
还有一个block参数 在这个block中
and it takes a block, and inside that block,
可以修改这三个属性
you can modify these three properties.
其实还可以做其他操作
There's actually a few others you can do,
但是这里
but these are the three main ones
我主要讲一下这三个属性
I'm going to talk about here.
就是这样的
So it looks like this.
叫做animationWithDuration
It's called animationWithDuration,
第一个参数代表这个动画
and the first argument is how long you want it to take
出现在屏幕上的时间
for this thing to appear on screen,
要记住 你所做的改变会立刻生效
remember that the change you make happens immediately.
所以如果你修改了alpha或者frame
So if you change the alpha or the frame,
或者transform 会立刻生效
or the transform, it instantly happens.
这个方法一执行就会生效
As soon as this method is executed.
这个方法总会立即返回
And this method returns immediately at all times, okay?
会立即执行block中的操作
It does what's in the block immediately.
但是会过一段时间才显示出来
But the appearance of it is going to happen over time.
如果修改了alpha 会淡入显示出来
Right? It's going to fade in, if it's alpha,
如果修改了frame 会移动过去
it's going to move over if it's the frame,
如果修改了transform 会进行旋转
it's going to rotate if it's the transform.
需要一段时间才能发生
Okay, that's going to happen over time.
duration表示需要多少时间来执行
Duration says how long to take to do that.
delay代表等待多长时间再开始执行
Okay? Delay is how long to wait to start doing it.
为什么会需要延迟呢
And why would you want a delay?
因为有时你需要连锁动画
Well, becomes sometimes you want to chain animations,
你想要先做一个两秒钟的动画
you want to do one animation first, that takes two seconds,
然后再做另外一个动画
then you want to do another animation after that.
有两种方法可以连接起来
Well, there's two ways to chain.
一是用第二个参数delay来延迟第二个动画发生
One is to delay the second one using this delay, second argument,
或者用completion block
or there's a completion block--
最下面的那个completion block
you see the completion block at the bottom there,
实际上 你可以在其中执行另一个动画
you can actually do another animation in that.
因为这个completion block
Because that completion block is called
会在动画完成时被调用
when the animation completes.
明白吗 还有options
Alright? Options.
我们会讲到所有options
We're going to talk about all the options,
动画有不少对应的options
and quite a few options for animating.
然后是这个最重要的animations参数
And then there's the all important animations argument.
它是一个block 没有参数
That is a block, you can see, it takes no arguments
也没有返回值
and has no return value.
在这个block中 你可以修改frame
In that block is where you change frame
还可以修改center center和frame是关联的
and you can also change center, center and frame are related,
还可以修改transform和alpha
and transform and alpha.
这是调用它的例子
Okay? So here's an example of calling it.
UIView 类方法animateWithDuration
So I'm saying UIView class method, animateWithDuration,
这个动画需要三秒
this animation is going to take 3 seconds,
我要做的是 不管我的视图是什么状态
and what I'm going to do is, whatever state my view is in,
我要让它淡出并消失
I'm going to make it fade out and disappear.
看到animation这个block了吗
Okay? So, you see in the animation block?
里面是myView.alpha=0.0
MyView dot alpha equals zero.
表示完全透明
That means fully transparent.
不管它现在的透明度是多少
Okay? So that is, whatever it's at now, okay, could be anything,
它的透明度要从当前值变为0
it's going to go from whatever it's at now to zero
在三秒内从屏幕上消失
in three seconds, on screen, okay?
在代码中 这是立即发生的
But in the code, this happens immediately.
视图的alpha值立即就变为0
Immediately the view has gone to alpha of zero,
只不过在屏幕上不会显示当前状态
it's just onscreen it's not showing what's currently the state,
会显示这个动画
it's showing this animation.
还要注意这里的完成处理程序
Okay? And notice the completion handler there.
完成处理程序block的参数
Okay? The argument to the completion handler's block
是一个BOOL值 代表动画是否结束
is a BOOL that says whether the animation finished.
这个动画为什么不会结束呢
Why wouldn't this animation finish?
可能会有其他动画开始了alpha动画
Well, some other animation might start animating alpha.
或者可能直接修改了alpha
Or someone might just set alpha.
如果有人干扰了alpha的变化
So if anyone interferes, with alpha,
那么完成处理程序就会被调用
then the completion handler will get called,
这个动画会被中断
this animation will get interrupted,
完成处理程序会被调用
the completion handler will get called,
但是BOOL值为NO
but the BOOL there will be no.
但如果没人中断它
But if nothing interrupts it,
alpha就会变为0
and the alpha goes all the way to zero,
然后这个完成处理程序会被调用
then this completion handler will be called,
参数为YES 代表动画完成了
and the argument will be yes, yes it completed,
如果动画完成了 我就要将视图
and if that happens, I'm then going to remove my view
从视图层级中移除
from the view hierarchy.
所以这行代码的意思就是淡出我的视图
So what this single line of code does is it fades out my view,
如果成功淡出了
and if it successfully fades it out,
就将它从视图层级中移除
removes it from the view hierarchy.
有问题吗
Question?
如果在下一行代码中
Did you, in the next line,
做了同样的操作
did kind of the same thing
但将alpha修改为了其他值
except changed the alpha to something else?
并将delay设为了3秒
And you had delay equals three seconds.
看起来就在二者交接的地方
It seems like it's right on the edge there,
它也许是在第一个结束之后发生的
maybe it happens after this one finishes,
也许是在结束之前发生的
or maybe it happens before.
是怎样的呢
Is there...?
好的 问题是 如果我又增加了一个动画
Yeah, so the question is, what if I have another animation
在下一行执行
that I execute on the very next line.
首先 假设我延迟了第一个动画
Well first of all, let's say I delay this one, right?
你的意思是延迟第一个调用
So you're saying delay this first call, put delay in there,
让delay为3 是吗
delay equals three or something?
是延迟执行第二个 这样它就...
Actually delay the second one, so that it has to--
好的 延迟第二个 3秒吗
Okay, delay the second one, exactly three seconds?
这样也是没问题的
Okay, so that will be fine
因为第一个动画
because the first one will finish instantly
会在第二个开始前立即结束
right before the second one starts, okay?
这种做法很常见
Because it's a common practice to do just exactly that.
让第一个动画执行3秒
Have something take three seconds,
然后让第二个动画延迟3秒执行
and then start the other one with a delay of three seconds,
没问题 可以运行
so yeah, it'll work.
还有一个... 错了
Here's another-- oops!
我可以做一下这个例子 但是...
Well I guess I can do that example, but anyway--
这是...
so that is--
大家明白这里是怎么回事吗
does everyone understand what's going on there?
就是这么简单 需要理解的主要是
It's really that simple, the main thing to understand is
alpha会被立刻设为0
that alpha would be set immediately to zero,
动画只是显示在屏幕上
it's just on screen that it will show.
好了 我们讲一下这些options选项
Alright, let's talk about some of the options.
第一个选项很有意思
The first one's an interesting option,
BeginFromCurrentState
BeginFromCurrentState.
如果你开启这个选项
So if you set this option on, okay, and when--
在选项列表中开启这个选项 意思就是
in the options list-- what this means is
如果还有一个正在执行的动画
if there is another animation that is going on
动画的对象与我想要的是同一个
that is animating the things I want to animate,
那么执行我的动画时 从它们的当前状态开始
then pick up from wherever they are when you do my animation.
所以如果我要修改alpha 让它逐渐消失
Okay? So if I'm doing that alpha thing and it's fading down
alpha变为0.2之类的
and it's down to 0.2, or something,
然后我让另一个动画开始执行
and then I issue another animation to start,
alpha增大到0.7
that goes up to 0.7 alpha,
如果开启了beginFromCurrentState
if I have beginFromCurrentState option on,
那么alpha就会从0.2变为0.7
then it will start at 0.2 and go up to 0.7.
如果不开启这个选项 就会从0开始
If I don't have this on, it will start at zero,
因为0才是alpha的真正的值 然后再增大到0.7
because zero is what the real alpha is, and go up to 0.7.
所以beginFromCurrentState可以用来
So beginFromCurrentState is a way
拦截其他动画
of intercepting other animations,
拦截它们
intercepting them, right?
在动画过程中拦截它们
In mid-flight.
之所以需要这样做
Okay? You need this because remember that
是因为设置动画参数后
when you set these animation parameters,
会立即生效
it happens immediately.
所以如果你想要拦截正在执行的动画
So if you want to intercept animation in flight
你需要设置一些选项
you need some option for the system
让系统检查视图的位置
to go check and see where the view is,
在让它显示在新位置之前
if it's flying across screen,
看它是否正在划过屏幕
before it sends it to a new place
当想让它淡出时 看它是否已经正在淡出
or if it's fading out, it fades at its new level.
通常情况下 这个选项都是开启的
It's very common to have that option on, actually.
可以看到 下面还有AllowUserInteraction
And then you see things like AllowUserInteraction,
动画正在执行时 这个视图中
do you want to allow gestures to happen in this view
是否允许手势发生
while it's in flight?
有的时候有用 有的时候没有
Sometimes that makes sense, sometimes not.
看到下面这些Curve开头的选项了吗
Down at the bottom, you see those curves?
CurveEaseIn和CurveEaseInEaseOut
CurveEaseIn, CurveEaseOut?
有时当你在屏幕上移动视图时
Sometimes when you move a view across screen
并不想直接将它提起来移动
you don't want it to just up and move,
你想要的是慢慢地提起来
you want it to kind of slowly pick up speed,
加速到最快 最后再减速
get up to full speed, and then slow down at the end.
这样动画看起来更平滑
It's a little smoother kind of animation
并不是生硬的移动视图
than just here's my view, mmmmm, that's a little, mmmmmm,
而是有一个加速减速的过程
you know, but mmmmmmmmmmmmm, okay?
效果更好 更平滑
Better. Smoother.
CurveEaseIn和CurveEaseInEaseOut就是用来控制的
So curve in, ease and out, that's for controlling that.
淡入淡出也是一样的 也可以这样处理
Okay? Same thing for fading, you could do it for fading as well.
尽管淡入淡出更倾向于线性运动
Though fading tends to be okay linear.
但是移动时用这个选项是很不错的
But moving definitely curving in and out is a pretty good idea.
大家可以回去看文档
So you can look in the documentation
看看这些选项的作用
and see what all these options do,
你可以重复动画
you can repeat animations,
让它们反复执行等等
have them go over and over and things like that.
这就是为这些特殊属性添加动画的方法
So that's how you animate those special properties, okay?
系统自动为他们添加动画 处理中间过程
And it animates them, it figures out all the in between.
即便你是同时执行多个动画
Even if you animate multiple of them at the same time.
移动 淡入淡出 旋转
It's moving, it's fading, it's rotating,
系统会自动插入
it will find, you know, it will interpolate all those points
变化路径上的所有点
all the way along automatically.
性能也很高
Okay? And pretty high performance, as well.
但有时 你在修改视图内容时
Okay. Sometimes though, you're changing your contents
用的不是这三个属性
of your view in a way that's other than those three things.
一个经典的例子就是卡牌游戏
The classic example here, the playing card.
当翻转卡牌时
When I'm flipping my playing card over,
我只设置了视图的一个属性
the only property I'm setting in my view
就是让faceUp等于YES
is faceUp equals yes, right?
这时卡牌就会翻到正面朝上
And now my card flips over to face up.
faceUp等于NO 卡牌翻到正面朝下
FaceUp equals no, now it flips over to down.
它本身并不是一个动画属性
So that's not an animatable property per se,
但是我想让这个视图通过动画
however, what I'd like to do is have the view change
实现从正面朝上到正面朝下的翻转
from face up to face down through some animation,
比如翻转卡牌
like flipping the card over,
或从一种状态渐变为另一种状态
or dissolving between the two.
换句话说 我要通过某些动画
In other words, I want to change the entire view
修改整个视图的状态
through some animation to a new state.
这就是这个方法的功能
And that's what this one is for.
transitionWithView
TransitionWithView.
transitionWithView的一个参数为view
So transitionWithView takes a view
即你的目标视图 比如playingCardView
that you want to do, like a playing card view,
还有一个duration参数
and it takes a duration.
代表从原有状态到新状态
How long it's going to take to go
需要多长时间
from the old state to the new state.
options和刚才的options类似
Options, again, similar to the other options,
但这里要用上面这里
but this is especially where you would specify the options
列出的选项
listed at the top there,
比如UIViewAnimationOptionsTransitionFlipFormLeft
like UIViewAnimationOptionsTransitionFlipFormLeft
代表我想让它翻过去
would mean I want this to flip over
或者选择交叉溶解 或者向上卷起
or cross dissolve, or curl up.
然后是animations 也是一个block
And then animations, again, is a block,
就是在这里设置faceUp
that's where you're going to set faceUp.
在这个block中 你可以对视图进行各种设置
In that block, you can set anything you want about the view
让它变为新状态
to make it be in its new state,
系统会应用这些修改
and the system will apply all those changes,
在屏外重绘新状态的视图
re-draw the view in the new state, off screen,
然后在二者之间进行转换
and then transition between the two.
原来的状态现在显示在屏幕上
The old state is on screen now,
变化后的视图在这边
and whatever your changes result in.
明白吗
Make sense?
有问题吗
Questions about that?
然后是completion 一样的 如果动画被中断了
And then completion, same thing, if you get interrupted somehow,
这里比较不容易中断
you know, it's harder to get interrupted on this one,
但是可以中断 然后完成处理程序就会被调用
but it can happen, then the completion handler gets called.
两种方式
Either way.
这个很好用
Okay? So this one will be great.
作业的一部分是要翻转卡牌
Part of your homework is to flip that card over,
你要用的就是这个方法
and this is the method you're going to want to use,
非常简单
so very, very straightforward.
如果你要修改视图层级
If you're changing the view hierarchy,
比如置换出一个视图
like you're swapping a view out, okay?
视图层级中有一个视图
You got a view in the view hierarchy
你将它换成了一个新视图
and you're swapping a new one in,
或者是隐藏一个视图 显示另外一个
or if you want to hide a view in favor of another view,
可以用这个transitionFromView toView方法
you can use this transitionFromView toView.
这个方法类似那个修改的方法
So this one is kind of like the other one in that you're changing,
但并不是只作用于一个视图
but instead of having a single view
改变它的状态 然后翻转它
that you're changing its state and then flipping it over,
这里是用另一个视图来替换这个视图
here you're replacing a view with another view.
但除此之外都很相似
Okay? But otherwise is very similar.
调用的对象基本一致 都是transition
It's even called almost the same thing, transition, right?
transitionFromView toView
Transition from view to view.
明白吗 好的
Okay? Alright.
这就是直接修改视图 属性
So that's it for direct changing of views, properties,
实现动画效果的方法
and making things happen. Okay?
下面我们要讲的是另外一种动画
The next kind of animation we're going to talk about,
是完全不同的系统 是iOS7的新增内容
which is a totally different system, new for iOS 7,
叫做dynamic animation动力动画
is called dynamic animation.
这是一个完全不同的概念
And this one's a completely different concept.
你要做的是 定义一些物理效果
Here, what you're going to do, is define a bunch of physics
然后应用于要添加动画效果的视图
that apply to all the views that you want to animate,
然后只要说 好了做吧
and then you're just going to say "Okay, do it!"
系统就会将这些物理效果应用于这些视图
And they're going to go have those physics apply to them.
有什么物理效果呢
So what kind of physics are we talking about here?
有重力 碰撞
We're talking about gravity, collisions,
作用力 等等
forces applied to them, things like that.
动画会一直运行
Okay? And they're just going to keep on animating
直到力量平衡
until the forces all balance out.
我们会看到是怎样的
Okay? And we'll see what that looks like.
想要实现它 这个API非常好用
The way we do this, this is a really nice API,
非常易用
very easy to use.
新建一个UIDynamicAnimator
You create a UIDynamicAnimator,
只需要创建一个
you just need to create one.
可以创建多个 但是一个较常见
You can do multiple, but just one--
是为了对这些行为进行分组
it's really for grouping these behaviors,
通常会用alloc/init
but usually create one dynamic animator
来创建UIDynamicAnimator
with alloc and init, basically.
我会演示的
I'll show you that.
然后向其中添加动力行为
And then you're going to add behaviors to it.
行为包括重力 碰撞 推动等等
Behaviors are like gravity, collisions, pushes,
这些叫做行为
those kinds of things, those are behaviors.
这些动力行为会应用于目标对象上
Things that are going to be applied to the things.
然后向其中添加内容
And then you put the things in there,
添加的是UIDynamicItem
and the things you put in there are UIDynamicItems,
代表它们响应或实现了那个协议
meaning they respond or they implement that protocol.
我也会演示的
I'll show you that.
将它们加进去时 动画会立刻开始执行
And the instant you put them in there, they'll start animating.
你不用告诉它运行 什么都不用说
You don't have to say run, you don't have to say anything,
只要动力动画者中有一个动力行为
immediately, any time there's an item
动力行为中有一个动力项
that's in a behavior that's in a dynamic animator,
动画就会立即开始 直到有力作用于它
it will start animating until the forces on it,
代表不用再移动了 这时就会停下来
meaning that it doesn't need to move, then it will stop.
我们详细讲一下
Okay? So let's look at all these things.
UIDynamicAnimator 可以直接用alloc/init
UIDynamicAnimator, you can just do alloc init,
但如果对象是视图
but when you're doing views,
如果要添加动画的是视图
if it's views that you want to animate,
就要用alloc/initWithReferenceView
you want to do alloc initWithReferenceView.
在initWithReferenceView中
Okay? And initWithReferenceView,
指定视图层级的顶级视图
you're specifying the top view of a view hierarchy,
所有要添加动画的视图都要在这个视图层级中
all the views you animate have to be in that view hierarchy,
也就是说 它们必须在这个层级中的某一层
in other words, they have to be somewhere,
是这个参考视图的子视图 或者是子视图的子视图
a subview of this reference view or a subview of that
或者再下面的子视图 层级可以很深
or a subview of that, as deep as you want to go,
但是你需要指定它的顶级视图
but you have to specify the top level view.
然后创建行为
Okay? Then you create these behaviors.
直接用alloc/init就可以了
Behaviors are just alloc init,
比如[UIGravityBehavior alloc] init
like UIGravityBehavior alloc init.
还有[UICollisionBehavior alloc] init
UICollisionBehavior alloc init,
然后将这些行为添加到animator中
and then you add these behaviors to the animator,
用addBehavior方法
using addBehavior,
是一个动力动画者方法
which is a dynamic animator method.
再简单不过了
Okay? Couldn't be simpler.
然后将动力项添加到动力行为中
And then, you add the items to the behaviors.
方法是什么
And you do that with?
在动力行为中使用addItem来添加
AddItem, in dynamic behavior.
动力项是一个id
So an item is just an id
实现了UIDynamicItem协议
that implements the protocol UIDynamicItem
就是下面这段
which you can see there below.
同样的 UIView实现了这个协议
And again, UIView implements that protocol,
所以通常情况下 加入的动力项是UIView
so usually the items we put in there are UIViews,
90%的情况下都是UIView
about 90 percent of the time.
在这门课上全部都是
100 percent of the time in this class,
作业中用到的也全部都是UIView
100 percent of the time in your homework,
我只要求大家实现视图动画
I'm only asking you to animate views,
但也可以为非视觉项添加动画
but you could animate completely non-visual items.
只要它们实现了这个协议
They could be-- as long as they implement this protocol,
就可以做任何想做的事情
they can do anything they want.
协议中有什么呢
So what's in the protocol?
有一个bounds
There's the bounds.
是动力项的bounds
That's again the bounds in the items world.
就像视图的bounds
It's like the view's bounds, right?
它自己的绘制坐标系
Its own drawing coordinate system.
注意bounds是只读的
Notice that's read only.
动力项可以通过变换 居中 移动等进行修改
Okay? It could be modified by the transform, centering,
大多数情况下是通过变换
moving the thing around, possibly, mostly the transform.
而bounds只是动力项的绘制区域
So the bounds, though, is just the drawing area for the item.
但是center中心 也就是动力项的位置
But the center, in other words, the position of the item,
以及transform变换 也就是旋转和缩放比例
and its transform, it's rotation and scale,
这两个属性是可读写的
those are read-write.
它们是可以被设置的
Those can actually be set.
显然是由animator设置的
They're obviously set by the animator,
动力动画者的作用
that's what the dynamic animator does is go
就是弄清楚动力项的中心 旋转和缩放比例的值
figure out what the center and rotation and scale should be.
你也可以设置它们
And you could set them too,
但是如果你要与animator同时进行设置
but if you do set them while the animator is also setting them,
需要调用这个方法updateItemUsingCurrentState
you have to call this method updateItemUsingCurrentState,
animator的当前状态
current state in the animator,
否则animator不会...
otherwise the animator will not--
它会忽略其他操作
will ignore anything that's going on.
所以如果你想要设置中心
Okay? So if you want to be setting the center,
如果你想要移动对象的时候
if you want to be moving the thing
animator也想要移动它
while the animator is also trying to move it,
换句话说 你想要和animator抗争一下
in other words, you want to fight it a little bit,
或者是animator正在移动它 而你想要让它旋转
or if it is moving it and you want to rotate it,
你需要用这个updateItemUsingCurrentState方法
you need to do this updateItemUsingCurrentState,
否则 出于性能方面的原因
otherwise it will assume, for performance reasons,
它会假设自己知道当前状态
that it knows the current state.
直到它的动画完成 一切操作完毕
Until it's done animating, until everything settles.
好了 就是这样
Okay? So that's it.
动力动画者 动力行为和动力项
Animator, behaviors and items.
这套系统中主要就是这三项内容
That's all there is in this system.
现在我们来讲一下动力行为
So now let's talk about some of these behaviors.
可用的具体行为
The concrete behaviors that are available.
首先是gravity重力
There's gravity.
重力行为默认是向下的
Okay? Gravity-- gravity behavior by default, gravity is down.
如果我拿起手机 是向下的
So if I'm holding my phone, it's down,
这说得通
which kind of makes sense
如果我这样拿起手机 显示内容应该是向下的
if I hold my phone up I kind of want things to go down,
但其实可以将其设为任意角度
but really it can be set to any angle.
可以让重力方向向上或向左
You can have the gravity up or to the left,
还可以从不同的方向
you can have multiple gravity pulling on things
向物体添加多个重力
from different directions.
实际上 如果向一个物体添加两个力
In fact, if you had two things pulling,
一个向上 一个向下
one from the top, one from the bottom,
这个物体就会飘在中间
the thing would just float in the middle
如果两个重力大小相等的话
if they have the same magnitude of gravity.
你可以设置重力大小
And you can set the gravity.
重力大小magnitude为1 代表1000p/s/s
Magnitude of 1 means a thousand points per second squared.
这是重力加速度
That's the acceleration due to gravity.
很像9.8m/s^2
That feels a lot like 9.8 meters per second squared
9.8m/s^2是实际重力加速度
which is acceleration due to real gravity.
换句话说 如果你竖起手机
So in other words, if you hold your phone up
让重力起作用
and let the gravity work,
感觉上 手机上物体的坠落速度
it kind of feels like it's falling about the same speed,
和现实物体的坠落速度一样
something in real life would happen,
这也是个很好用的整数
and it's also a very nice round number,
1000p/s^2
a thousand points per second squared.
但是要知道它就像是重力
Okay? But understand, it's just like gravity,
是某个方向上的重力加速度
it's an acceleration in a certain direction.
collision碰撞非常酷
Collision is really cool.
碰撞指的是 当碰撞行为中的动力项
Collision just means the items inside of the collision behavior,
碰到一起的时候 会互相弹开
if they bump into each other, they'll bounce off each other,
和现实中的碰撞效果类似
like a real world collision,
你可以指定弹力大小
and you can specify the elasticity
它们的弹性大小
and how bouncy they are,
甚至可以为二者定义不同的密度
and even you can define the density of one versus another,
密度大的一方可以把密度小的撞走
so a really dense one will smash another one out of the way,
这些都是可以自定义的
all definable.
还可以设置边界
You can also set boundaries.
可以按需要 设置任意UIBezierPath
So any UIBezierPath that you want to come up with,
将它添加到碰撞行为中
you can put it in your collision behavior
物体碰到它会弹开
and things will bounce off it.
可以是圆形 方形等等
So it can be round, it can be square, whatever,
当物体碰到它时会弹开
and things will bounce off it when they hit it.
你还可以将参考视图的边界
Also you can set the boundaries of the reference view
也设置为有弹性的边界
to be bouncy boundaries as well
方法是将translatesReferenceBoundsIntoBoundary设为YES
by saying translatesReferenceBoundsIntoBoundary equals yes,
这样物体碰到参考视图的边缘就会弹开
and then things will bounce off the edges of the reference view,
也就是动力动画者的顶级视图
the top level view in the dynamic animator. Okay?
collisionMode决定了动力项
So, the collisionMode determines whether the items
是相互碰撞弹开 还是只从边界碰撞弹开
bounce off each other or just off the boundaries.
明白吗
Alright?
吸附行为
Attachment behaviors.
通过它 可以将一个动力项
Okay, this is the way to attach an item
吸附到一个固定锚点或另外一个动力项上
to a fixed point or to another item.
这里有一点要记住
Now one thing to remember about this,
如果我将一个动力项连接到一个锚点上
if I hook an item up to a point,
并不意味着这个动力项就不会移动了
that does not mean that item is not going to move.
如果我将一个动力项连接到这个锚点上 动力项在这里
Okay? If I hook it up to this point and I have an item here,
这时重力起作用了会怎样
right, and gravity happens?
动力项会这样摆动
My item is going to go like this...it's going to swing.
因为吸附行为只是将两个对象连接起来
Because the attachment is just attaching the two things,
锚点和动力项
the point and the item.
并没有吸附到背景上 对吧
It's not attaching to the background, okay?
如果我移动了这个锚点 动力项也会随之移动
And also if I move the point, the thing will stay with it
会在后面摆动之类的
and it will kind of swing around behind it.
演示中会看到这部分
And we'll see this in the demo, okay?
吸附行为是将动力项吸附到锚点上
So attachment is attaching the thing to a point.
还可以吸附两个动力项
You can also attach two items.
如果这样吸附了两个动力项 然后重力作用向下
If I attach two items like this and I gravity down,
它们就会撞到
they're going to go bam!
它们会保持同样的距离
They'll stay the same distance apart,
但是会直接掉下来
but they're just going to go straight down
因为重力依旧会作用于它们
because gravity will still be applying to them as well.
连接只是能够让它们在一起
Right? And the connection just keeps them together.
吸附行为有点不同
The attachment behavior is a little different
不用alloc/init
in that you don't alloc init,
而是在初始化时指定吸附对象
you actually specify the attachment at init time.
所以用alloc/initWithItem与另一个动力项吸附
So alloc initWithItem, alloc init with other item,
还有一种也是吸附动力项
there's also some versions where you can attach items,
但吸附点不是中心
where the attachment point
而是一个偏移量
instead of being the center is offset.
这样动力项是悬着的
And that will make things kind of hang
动力项在旋转时是倾斜的
if the items rotate, they'll kind of tilt,
因为它的吸附点不是中心
okay, because you're not grabbing them in the middle,
而是偏向一侧的
you're grabbing them on the side,
这样你可以做出很酷的效果
so you can make some pretty cool effects.
要注意 吸附行为还有一点很棒
The other thing to notice about attachments that's cool
就是两个动力项之间的长度是可写的
is that the length between the two items is writeable.
比如说 你要捏合缩放
So for example, let's say you were pinching.
可以改变它们之间的长度
You could change the length
这两个吸附的动力项会靠近在一起
and those two attached items would move closer together.
即便你设置了
Okay? So even though you set it up
让这个动力项吸附到这个锚点上
as this item attach to this point
或者让两个动力项互相吸附
or these items attach to each other,
如果你将二者间长度缩小
if you change the length to be smaller,
它们就会互相靠近 这很棒
they'll move toward each other, okay, that which is cool,
锚点也是一样的
and the same thing with the anchor point.
如果你移动了锚点
If you move the anchor point around,
它的吸附项也会移动
the attachment is still there
跟在锚点的后面
and the thing will follow around, right?
再加上应用的其他行为
With other behaviors applying to it.
有问题吗
Question?
这个吸附长度是一个确定值吗
Is that attachment length, is that an exact value,
还是像是...
like it would be with like when they're attached or--
你的意思是像铁棒吗
Iron, like an iron bar you mean?
对 是像铁棒呢 还是像线绳呢
Yeah, like iron bar or string?
问题是 这个连接是像铁棒呢
Okay, so the question is, is it like an iron bar
还是像线绳呢
or is it more like a string?
实际上 它像是一个弹簧
And actually what it is, it's like a spring, okay?
你移动它的时候
So it actually as you move it around,
比如向上移动 它会弹上来
like if I move it up, it will "Whoom!"
弹起来
spring up.
你可以控制它的阻尼大小和震荡频率
And you can control the damping and oscillation of that.
默认情况下 是像一个铁棒
By default, it's an iron bar.
阻尼大小和振荡频率的默认值
Okay? So the damping and oscillation are set
让它不会发生振荡
so that it does not oscillate,
但是你可以自己设置 让它跟着振荡
but you can set it so as you follow it around it kind of--
非常酷
It's very, very cool.
做作业的时候
So you can play with all of those
大家可以都试一下
when you are doing your homework.
速甩行为是将一个动力项甩到一个位置
Snap behavior snaps an item to a location,
不只是让它飞过去
but it does more than just have it fly there.
确实是飞过去 速度很快
It does fly there, rather rapidly I might add.
达到目标位置之后 可以想象成
When it gets there, though, you can imagine that
动力项四角有四个弹簧
there's four springs attached to the item in the corners,
稍微离开一点
a little ways out,
动力项到达目标位置时会来回振动
so the thing gets there and it goes "Doinggg",
就像弹簧振动 像这样
kind of springs, like this.
你可以指定振动的大小
And you can specify how much it does that.
为什么要这样做呢
Why does it do that?
因为你要给用户反馈
That's because you want to give feedback to the user,
让他们知道自己刚移动了它
oh, I just moved this.
我们并不想让它到了位置立马停住
So you don't want it to just go "Blip!"
而是让它晃动一下
You want it to go "Hmmmm," you know,
让动力项弹跳一下
and it kind of gives them just a moment's springiness,
让用户明白
so it's like "Oh, okay."
这是个很好的动画
So that's good animation,
速甩行为很常用
the snap behavior very common.
还有推动行为
Also you have push behavior,
你可以推一下
which is you can push,
推一下对象 它就开始移动了
push an object and it will start moving.
尤其是 如果你没有添加重力
So especially if you don't have gravity,
推动可能就是让物体移动的原因
this might be what causes things to move, you push it
它移动过去 动力项有摩擦力
and it moves across and then these items have friction,
相互碰撞的时候 密度不同
they have density when they collide with each other,
大家可以回去看看推动行为的文档
so push, you can read about push
看一下如何指定角度和推力大小等等
and how you specify the angle and the magnitude and all that.
关于行为 还有一件事是
Okay? So another thing about behaviors is you want to be able
在设置摩擦力 弹力和密度等
to set this friction, elasticity, the density,
设置我们刚才说过的这些属性时
all these things that we're talking about,
我们想要将其设置到动力项上
you want to set them on the items
与行为无关
independent of the other behaviors, okay?
如果我设置了摩擦力
So if I have friction, I want it to apply,
不管动力项移动是因为重力还是碰撞
whether it's gravity that's causing the thing to move,
摩擦力应该是一致的
or whether a collision caused it to move.
所以摩擦力 密度等属性
So we don't put the friction and the density and stuff like that
不是在碰撞行为或者重力行为中进行设置
in collision behaviors or gravity behaviors,
而是放在它自己的行为中 叫做动力项行为
we put it in its own behavior called the items behavior.
对应的行为类叫做UIDynamicItemBehavior
So there's a class of behavior called UIDynamicItemBehavior.
如果你想要设置这些属性
Okay? And so if you want any of these things,
比如不允许它旋转
like you don't want to allow it to rotate,
不想让视图旋转
you don't want the view to be able to rotate,
不知道作业中是怎样的
which I don't know if you're doing homework
有时需要 有时不需要
sometimes you might want that, sometimes not,
或者是想要指定对象的摩擦力或弹力
or you want to specify the friction or the bounciness of this object,
新建一个UIDynamicItemBehavior
you create a UIDynamicItemBehavior
将动力项也添加到其中
and add the items to that as well.
所以动力项既是重力行为的一员
So the item would be a member of the gravity behavior,
又是碰撞行为的一员
it might be of the collision behavior,
还是UIDynamicItemBehavior的一员
and it's also a member of a UIDynamicItemBehavior.
它控制着全部选项
Okay? And this controls all its options.
你可以把这看做是动画选项
So you can think of this as kind of like the animation options,
但其实更像是
but really it's more like the behavior of the--
动力项的内在行为
the intrinsic behavior of that item.
它的密度是多少
Okay? What is its density?
不管起作用的是哪个行为
You want that to be the same
密度都是一样的
no matter what behavior is acting on it.
还可以用UIDynamicItemBehavior
You can also find out information about
获取动力项的信息
what's going on with the item using UIDynamicItemBehavior.
比如linearVelocityForItem方法
It has methods like linearVelocityForItem.
会告诉你这个动力项
It will tell you the velocity of this item
在不同方向上的速度
in different directions.
在接管动画时很好用
Which is really cool for if you want to take over animation,
动力动画系统让动力项开始移动
the dynamic animation system started this thing moving,
现在你想接管 让它继续移动
and now you want to take over and keep it moving,
换一个方向移动之类的
maybe in some other direction or something like that.
可以获取当前移动速度
You can find out how fast is it moving right now,
然后以该速度继续移动
and then continue having it move at that speed.
角速度也是一样的
Same thing with angular velocity.
每秒旋转的弧度是多少
How fast it's rotating in radians per second. Okay?
动力行为...
Dynamic behaviors also--
UIDynamicBehavior
the UIDynamicBehavior is the base class
是重力行为 碰撞行为等的基类
for gravity behavior, collision behavior, all these,
你也可以自己创建子类
you can also create your own subclass,
通常情况下 只要在实现文件中
and usually when you do your implementation,
将其他行为添加为子行为
just adds other behaviors as child behaviors.
UIDynamicBehavior有一个方法
So there's a method in UIDynamicBehavior
叫做addChildBehavior
called addChildBehavior,
你可以添加重力行为 碰撞行为 UIDynamicItemBehavior
and you can add a gravity, collision, UIDynamicItemBehavior,
将其作为子行为
as sub-behaviors.
这很常见 只是为了整理API
And this is very common to do, just to clean up your API,
将一起使用的行为放到它们自己的类中
to group behaviors that go together, into their own class.
它们自己的UIDynamicBehavior子类中
Okay? Their own UIDynamicBehavior subclass,
里面通常都是子行为
and all that thing usually has is child behaviors
也许还有几个API
and then maybe a little bit of API
用来以某种方法添加项
to add the items in a certain way
或用其他方法将它们关联起来
or have them interrelate in some other way.
此外 所有UIDynamicBehavior
Okay? What is more, all behaviors, all UIDynamicBehaviors,
重力 碰撞 自定义行为等等
gravity, collision, your own custom ones, whatever,
都知道自己所在的动力动画者是什么
they know what dynamic animator they are in.
它们有一个属性叫做dynamicAnimator
They have a property called dynamicAnimator
可以返回它们所在的动力动画者的信息
which will say what dynamic animator they're in,
UIDynamicBehavior有一个
and there's kind of a view controller life cycle thing
类似于视图控制器生命周期的机制
of UIDynamicBehaviors,
只有一个方法
which only has one method in it,
willMoveToAnimator
willMoveToAnimator.
当行为移动到动画者中
So that gets called every time it gets moved to an animator
或从动画者中移除时
or out of an animator.
这个方法会被调用 参数为nil
So this would be called with nil.
可以通过这个方法知道
Okay? So that way you can find out
你的行为当前是否正在执行动画
whether your behavior is currently being animated or not,
是由哪个动画者执行
and by which animator. Okay?
关于行为 我还要讲最后一点
And the last thing I'm going to tell you about behaviors,
非常棒的属性 是一个block 叫做action
really cool property is a block called action,
这个block没有返回值 也没有参数
this block returns nothing and takes no arguments,
是基本的block
so it's basic block.
要用这个block 只要先说行为名称
This block you provide, you just say my whatever behavior,
重力行为 碰撞行为等等
gravity behavior, collision behavior, whatever,
然后是.action 等于一个block
dot action equals a block
每次这个行为引发动画变化时
it will execute that block every time
都会执行那个block
this behavior causes animation change.
这个block会被调用很多次
Okay? So this is called a lot,
比如 重力作用下 物体向下时
as gravity pulls the thing down,
每次移动 哪怕只移动了1像素 它也会被调用
every time it moves, even a pixel, this thing gets called.
如果发生碰撞
Okay? If a collision happens,
物体移动了 这个block就会被调用
and it moves that causes it to move, this will get called.
可以通过这个方法参与到动画中
Okay? So this is a way to get in there and get involved.
使用它的时候要负起责任
Now, you have a responsibility when you get in there,
不要在action中执行资源消耗过大的操作
don't do anything really expensive in action
否则动画会变得磕磕绊绊的
or your animation will get all jerky.
不要做资源消耗过大的操作
Okay? You do not want to do something expensive
比如绘制很多内容
like draw too much,
可以绘制少量内容
but you can draw a little bit.
我会在周三的演示中讲到的
And we'll show in the demo on Wednesday, we'll get to the part
我会设置一个action 绘制少量内容
where I'll set an action that draws a little bit,
让大家看得更清楚
so that we can see things a little better,
可以看到这个action 非常好用
and you can see this, really nice to be able to set this.
这是一个简单的连接方法
Okay? So this is a simple little hook to get involved
用来参与到行为引发的动画中
with the animation that these behaviors are causing to happen.
懂了吗
Okay?
好了 我们进入演示部分
Alright. So let's do this demo.
下面这个列表中的内容 稍后都会演示
All that what to look for, you can look on later,
放这里只是为了让大家看到
just to make sure you actually saw this.
这个示例叫做Dropit
This demo is called "Dropit."
基本上 就是让方块视图掉下来
And basically going to drop views, squares, down,
堆积在底部
and they're going to collect at the bottom,
集满一行之后 就会炸掉这一行
and when a whole row collects, I'm going to blow them up.
有点像俄罗斯方块
Kind of like Tetris.
知道俄罗斯方块吗
You know Tetris?
将各种方块放到一起 拼成一行后
You put the blocks in and when they fit and you get a row,
这一行就消掉了
boom, the row disappears.
我们要做的就是这个
We're going to do that. Okay?
我们不会用俄罗斯方块之类的
We're not going to use Tetris squares and stuff like that,
这只是一个演示 只有45分钟
this is a demo, I only have like 45 minutes to do,
我们就用方块来代替
but we'll do blocks instead.
但在这段时间内
But the main thing I just want to show you everything I can
我想演示的主要是动画的各种相关内容
in that amount of time, about animation.
我们要新建一个应用 关掉这个
So we're going to make a new app here, let's get rid of that.
不需要这个
Don't need that.
新建一个项目
We're going to create a new project.
我要叫它...
I'm going to call this project--
这里我就快速带过了
I'm going to go quite fast now
这部分大家都已经知道了
through most of this stuff that you already know how to do.
我要叫它Dropit
So I'm going to do Dropit,
视图控制器也叫Dropit
I'm going to call the view controller also Dropit.
保存在主目录Developer下
Okay? We'll put it in home directory Developer.
这就是我们的Dropit
Here's our Dropit.
你们知道的 我喜欢把这些移走
You know me, I always like to move these out of the way.
好了 这是我的storyboard
Alright. So here's my storyboard.
我要用一个通用UIView来包含这个游戏
I'm going to use a generic UIView to contain my game.
这个小的掉落游戏
Okay? My little dropping game.
可以在self.view中做这个掉落游戏
I could do all this dropping in self dot view here,
但并不是个好主意
but it's usually a bad idea,
如果我想加一个分数
because what if I ever want to add a score
或者加一个按钮之类的呢
or another button or something like that,
我希望游戏是在一个稍小的空间中
I want my game then to be in a little smaller space,
大家的作业中也要这样做
and you're going to want to do that for your homework as well.
我只要直接拖出一个通用UIView
So I'm just going to drag out a generic UIView.
我总是找不到它
I always have trouble finding it.
在这呢
Yep, there it is.
我只要把这个通用UIView拖到这里
So I'm just going to drag this generic UIView in here,
创建一个指向它的输出口
and I'm going to create an outlet to it,
我要加它gameView
I'm going to call it my gameView.
只要按住control键拖到这里 叫做gameView
So just control, drag, out here and call it gameView.
它是一个通用UIView
And it's a generic UIView.
不是自定义的
It's no custom thing.
我只是想让它成为边界
But I just want it to be the bounds,
这样如果我想在里面增加UI之类的话
and I can move these bounds in from the edge
就可以将边界从边缘移进来
if I wanted to put some other UI in there or whatever.
游戏视图有了
So now I have my game view.
我还要再加一个点击手势
And I'm also going to have a tap gesture,
拖出一个点击手势
so let's drag out a tap gesture.
每次点击屏幕时
So that every time I tap on this,
就会有一个方块掉落下来
I'm going to add another square to drop.
将它放到游戏视图中
Okay? So I'm going to put this on my game view.
这是我的点击手势
Here's my tap gesture right here.
control拖动到右边这里 我要叫它tap
Control drag this out, I'll call it tap.
增大点空间
Get some more space here for us.
每次点击游戏视图时
So every time that you tap on my game view,
就会掉下一个正方形
I'm going to drop another, drop another full square
就像俄罗斯方块那样
that falls down like a Tetris kind of thing.
打错了
Oops. Oops.
drop 好了
Drop. Okay?
这就是这个方法的作用
So that's what this method is going to do,
添加一个视图
it's just going to add a view.
正好我可以演示一下
So this is also a chance for me to show you
如何用代码创建UIView
how to create a UIView in code,
希望大家都做过了
which hopefully you've all done that
因为作业中有一部分
because you've done the part of the homework
就是要完成自定义视图
that's the custom view,
但是如果你没做过 正好学一下
but if you haven't, here you go.
我要先创建frame
I'm going to actually create the frame first.
所以我要设置frame
So I'm gonna do this frame.
我要将frame的原点设为CGPointZero
I'm going to have the frame origin start out at CGPointZero,
然后我会改变x轴原点
but then I'm going to change the x origin.
掉落是从顶部开始的
So I'm going to have that drop start out at the top
然后我会选取x轴上的任意一点
and then I'm just gonna put in a random spot across the x.
大小呢 我要定义一个小的...
The size, I'm going to define a nice little--
添加一个static值
let's do a static.
static const CGSize 叫它DROP_SIZE 等于
Static, const, CGSize, we'll call this DROP_SIZE equals
我要将大小设为40*40
and I'll make it like 40 by 40,
我将它设为静态常量
but I'm going to make this be static const
而不是设为属性之类的
as opposed to making it be a property or something
因为我现在不想添加代码
because I don't want to write the code right now
来处理其他对象修改大小的情况
to deal with the fact that someone changes this,
那样我可能就要重绘整个视图
because I probably have to re-draw my whole thing
显示更小的方块
to have smaller squares, right?
或者类似的效果
Or something like that.
很棒 值得实现
Which is cool, be great to do,
但是时间有限 我就不做了
but just with time constraints I'm not going to do that.
让frame的大小等于这个DROP_SIZE
So I'm going to have the frame size be this drop size.
我是在创建一个小的掉落视图
So I'm creating a little drop view, okay,
我想让它的大小是这样的
and that's the size I want it to be.
然后设置随机...
So here I'll do my random--
我们这样做吧
actually let's go ahead and do this...
转到这里
let's go to here.
在x轴上随机选取一点
Let's go just pick a random place along the x axis,
用arc4random 然后取模于
so I'm going to do arc4random, and we're going to mod
self.gameView.bounds.size.width
that by the self dot gameView dot bounds dot size dot width,
得到x轴上的随机一点
so somewhere along some random spot along there.
我还要让它们排列起来
And I'm also going to make it be lined up
这样掉落的方块就是在格子里
so the drops are, you know, in a grid.
直接除以DROP_SIZE.width
So I'm just going to divide by the DROP_SIZE dot width,
然后做乘法
and then I'm going to multiply by saying
frame.origin.x=x*DROP_SIZE.width
frame dot origin dot x equals x times DROP_SIZE dot width,
我这里用了除法 这是一个整数
so you see here, I've divided it here, this is an int,
这样就会排列在一行上
so it's basically going to do a floor, right?
我选择了一个整数 然后乘回去
I've picked an int and just multiply it back,
将它放在了一个随机点上
that puts it at a random spot across,
然后创建一个视图 方法是
and then I create a view just by saying
dropView=[UIView alloc] initWithFrame
dropView equals UIView alloc initWithFrame,
这是视图的指定初始化方法
which is the designated initializer for view,
指定这个frame 然后...
and I'll specify this frame, and then I'm just going--
我要将dropView的背景色
I'm going to set the dropView's background color
设为随机色
to be a random color.
我正好有randomColor方法的代码
Okay, I happen to have a little snippet for that, randomColor.
randomColor是从这五个颜色中随机选择一个
Okay, so randomColor just picks one of five random colors,
这五个
okay, right here.
然后再加上
And then let's just go ahead
self.gameView addSubview:dropView
and self dot gameView, addSubview, dropView.
想要实现掉落方块就是这么简单
Okay? So it's as simple as that to drop something on here,
如果我没忘记步骤 都做对了的话
so unless I've forgotten something or doing something wrong,
我们运行一下
let's go ahead and run.
每点击一下 就会出现一个方块 很好
Every time I tap, we get another one, so that's great.
都堆积在顶部 不错
They're collecting at the top. That's nice.
现在我们添加重力 让它们掉下来
Now we're going to add some gravity so that they fall down.
为它们添加动画 让它们掉落下来
Okay? Animated, so they fall down.
怎么做呢
So how do we do that?
非常简单 只要新建一个动画者
Very simple, we're just going to create an animator,
添加一个属性 strong nonatomic
have a property which is strong nonatomic,
是一个UIDynamicAnimator
which is a UIDynamicAnimator,
再添加一个属性 strong nonatomic
and I'm also gonna have a property which is strong, nonatomic,
是一个UIGravityBehavior 叫做gravity
which is a gravity behavior, I'll call it gravity.
出于某些原因 名字尽量短小
Keeping these names short kind of for a reason,
但你也可以叫它gravityBehavior
but you might want to call it gravity behavior.
我要在这里加一些延迟实例化
I'm going to go ahead and do some lazy instantiation here,
先获取一个动力动画者
so let's get our dynamic animator,
如果没有动画者 就创建一个
if not animator, then I want to create one,
否则就直接返回它
otherwise I'm going to return it.
创建动画者的方法 我刚才讲了
Okay? So as I said when we create the animator,
[UIDynamicAnimator alloc] initWithReferenceView
it's just UIDynamicAnimator alloc initWithReferenceView
参考视图就是gameView
and the reference view is just our gameView, right?
我刚才拖出的那个通用视图
That view that I dragged out, that generic view,
参考视图可以是通用视图
it's perfectly fine for that reference view
完全没问题
to be a generic view.
重力行为这里也类似
And then the gravity one similar kind of deal,
如果没有动力行为 就创建一个
if the gravity is not set, then we'll create it
有的话就直接返回
and we'll return it,
创建重力行为的方法非常简单
and creating a gravity thing is very simple,
_gravity=[[UIGravityBehavior alloc] init]
we just say gravity equals UIGravityBehavior alloc init.
这里我还要做一个操作
Okay? I'm going to do one other thing here too
self.animator addBehavior
is I'm going to say self dot animator addBehavior.
只要有人请求重力行为
Okay? So any time someone asks me for the gravity thing,
我就会将它加到动画者中
I'm going to add it to my animator.
这部分只会执行一次
This is going to only happen once, right?
因为这是延迟实例化
Because this is my lazy instantiator,
很好 我想要的就是这样
so that's good, that's exactly what I want.
还可以在这里面设置其他内容
I could also in here set things
比如重力大小magnitude
like the gravity's magnitude, right?
我可以不用1.0 设一个小点的重力大小
So I could say light gravity instead of 1.0,
稍微轻一点
a little lighter or whatever. Okay?
现在我有了动画者和重力行为
So now I have an animator, I have a gravity behavior,
现在我只要将我刚才创建的dropView
all I need to do now is add this dropView,
添加进来就可以了
okay, that I created to that,
self.gravity addItem:dropView
so I'm just going to say self dot gravity addItem, my dropView.
做完这一步之后
Okay? So now that the instant I do that
动画立刻就会开始
it's going to start animating.
我们来看一下
So let's take a look at that.
可以看到 随着我的点击 动画马上开始运行
So you can see as I click they immediately start animating.
看到了吗
Okay?
抱歉 跑掉了
And sorry,
现在它们直接掉出屏幕了 是吧
but they're falling off the bottom, okay?
这可不好 我希望它们堆积在底部
So that's not so good, I want them to stop at the bottom.
为此我只需要一个碰撞行为 非常简单
So to do that, I just need a collision behavior, very easy,
在上面这里加上property (strong, nonatomic)
just go up here, property, strong, nonatomic,
UICollisionBehavior 我要叫它collider
UICollisionBehavior, collider, I'm going to call it.
在collider里
And my collider,
如果没有设置collider 我就会创建一个
if my collider is not set, then I'll set it,
如果有就直接返回
return the collider,
这段代码我真应该提前敲好
I really should have a snippet for that kind of thing.
周五讲座的时候约翰应该演示过了吧
I think Johan showed that in the Friday section.
_collider=[[UICollisionBehavior alloc] init]
So that equals UICollisionBehavior alloc init,
这里我还要将bounds设为YES
and here I'm also going to set the bounds to yes.
我要让这个collider用参考视图的bounds
So I'm going to have this collider use the bounds
作为自己的bounds
of the reference view as its bounds, okay,
一行代码就够了
so it's a one line thing to get that in there,
但是我还可以加上一个UIBezierPath
but I could make, you know, a nice UIBezierPath,
沿着底部放置
you know, like down along the bottom, whatever I want,
但是这里用这个translation
but it suits my purposes here
就可以满足我的需求了
just to use the whole translation,
这里也是一样的
and I'm going to do the same thing here,
self.animator addBehavior: _collider
self dot animator addBehavior, this collider.
这样它就添加到了动画者中
Okay, so it gets added to the animator.
这里也需要将
So again, I need to add any items
受collider影响的动力项
that I want to be affected by the collider
添加到collider中
to the collider, and now it's going to--
这样做之后
as soon as I do that,
如果有东西撞到了它 就会运行碰撞动画
if something hit it, it would start colliding.
我们看一下
Alright? So let's take a look at that.
它们掉到底部停下来了
Okay, so hopefully the drop,
注意 它们反跳了一下
notice they have a little bounce to them,
稍微跳起来了一点
a little bounce in their step.
注意 它们斜了一点
Now notice that they tilt a little.
为什么会这样
Okay. Why does that happen?
两个方块落到下面的时候
Well, on the way down, the two they landed,
一个弹起来 另一个撞到了它
one was bouncing and the next one hit it,
就会有一点现实的反作用力
and there was a little bit of real world bounce to it.
如果我们做的是俄罗斯方块
Now, probably if we're building a Tetris game,
我们并不想让它旋转 偏离中心
we don't want them to rotate and get off center like that,
所以我们可以禁用旋转
so we would have to A, not allow rotation probably
或者用对它们进行网格排列
and B, we might want to grid them up.
示例中可能讲不到了
I don't think we're going to get that in the demo,
周三我可能会讲一下
but maybe on Wednesday I'll get to that,
我会告诉大家实际上要怎么做
I'll post how you would actually do that.
我们要做的就是 当它们碰撞时
Okay? And all we're going to do is when they collide,
让它们排列对齐
we're going to have them line themselves up.
我们会在周三讲到这部分
Okay? So we'll do that later on Wednesday.
注意 这两个行为关系紧密
Okay, notice that I have these two very related behaviors,
重力和碰撞行为
gravity and collider.
它们常一同出现
They really go together.
这里我们要
Okay? So this is where I might want
创建一个自定义行为
to create a custom UI behavior.
我们来快速做一下
So let's do that real quick.
在文件菜单下选择新建文件 新建一个类
I'm just going to go file, new file, okay, new class,
这个类是一个UIDynamicBehavior
and this class is going to be a UIDynamicBehavior.
我要叫它DropitBehavior
And I'm going to call it the DropitBehavior.
这是我新建的一个行为
Okay? And that is going to be a new behavior I'm creating
包括重力行为和碰撞行为
that's going to have the gravity and the collider
以及其他行为等子行为
and eventually some more things as child behaviors.
点击下一步 选择保存位置
Okay? So let's hit next, where we want to put it,
很好 出来了
this is all good, here it is.
这就是我的DropitBehavior
Okay? Here's my DropitBehavior,
在这个DropitBehavior中
and all I'm going to do in this DropitBehavior
我要定义两个方法
is I'm going to define a couple of methods here,
addItem方法允许添加UIDynamicItem
addItem, which allows you to add UIDynamicItem,
注意这里我用了协议的语法
notice I'm using this protocol syntax,
还要添加一个移除动力项的方法
and then I'm also going to let you remove an item.
在DropitBehavior中 我就要实现这些方法
And that's all I'm gonna implement in my DropitBehavior
但我要重写它的初始化方法
except for I'm going to override its init.
我要在init中做什么呢
Okay, so what am I going to do in its init?
instancetype init
So instancetype, init,
self=[super init]
I'm going to do self equals super init,
这是UIDynamicBehavior的init方法
so that's UIDynamicBehavior's init.
然后是return self
Alright? And then return self,
在中间这里
and then in between here
我只要添加子行为
all I'm gonna do is add child behaviors
重力行为gravity和碰撞行为collider
for the gravity and the collider,
我就直接复制粘贴了
which I'm actually going to copy and paste.
省点时间
Save ourselves a little time,
这是它们的延迟实例化
here's nice little lazy instantiation of these,
我们... 点错了
and let's go grab the-- oops,
复制它们的输出口 加到这里
let's grab the outlets for these, add those.
抱歉 我一直点错
Oops, sorry, I keep clicking on the wrong button.
这里加上@interface DropitBehavior()
Okay, so this is at sign interface, DropitBehavior,
粘贴到这里
oops, paste, hello, paste.
粘贴好了 很好
And okay so we've got those, that's good.
至于这行代码 我们不用再将它添加到动画者中了
These lines, we're not going to add it to the animator
因为我们要把整个行为添加到动画者中
because we're going to add this whole behavior to the animator,
所以我们可以删掉这两行代码
so we can get rid of those.
把addItem放到这里
And in addItem, which we'll put right here.
我们就直接复制粘贴
Actually let's go ahead and copy and paste
这两个方法
these two things that we want.
addItem和removeItem
AddItem and removeItem.
这里我要做的就是
Okay, all I need to do here
将它们添加到子行为中
is add them to each of my sub behaviors,
用addItem将动力项添加到gravity中
so I'll do addItem to my gravity
添加到collider中
and addItem to my collider.
移除动力项也是一样的
And I'll do the same thing for remove.
但是这里要改成remove
Okay, except we want this to be remove.
这是一个常见的模式
Okay. So this s a common pattern here, you know,
你创建一个动力行为
you create basically a dynamic behavior
添加子行为等等
that has child behaviors and in the add,
可以用addItem
I mean you also have addItems,
或者initWithItem等等
you might have initWithItem, whatever,
然后在这里 添加子行为
and then here, we're going to add child behaviors,
gravity和collider
the gravity and the collider.
我们新建了一个类
Okay? So we've created a new class here,
它是UIDynamicBehavior的一个子类
it's a sub-class of UIDynamicBehavior.
我们可以向其添加动力项
We can add items to it,
与向gravity和collider添加动力项是一样的
just like we added items to our gravity and our collider,
它的实现就是添加子行为
and its implementation is merely to have a sub,
这些子行为
these little sub behaviors.
非常简单
Okay? Very, very simple.
回到控制器
And we go back to our controller here,
这里不再需要用单独的行为
we need to, instead of having the individual ones,
只要添加一个自定义行为就可以了
now we're just going to have a drop it--
#import DropitBehavior
sorry, pound sign import, DropitBehavior.
添加一个DropitBehavior
It's going to have a DropitBehavior,
这里也用延迟实例化
okay, we'll put a little lazy instantiation for this one too.
这里的alloc/init
so there's alloc init,
会调用我们刚才编写的那个init方法
that's going to call that other init that we just did.
self.animator addBehavior:_dropitBehavior
We'll do self dot animator addBehavior our dropitBehavior,
然后只要返回_dropitBehavior
alright, and then we'll just return our dropitBehavior
就像这样
like that.
这里不用再两次添加动力项了
And now, down here, we don't have to add these separately,
直接像这样用dropitBehavior addItem就可以了
we're just gonna say dropitBehavior addItem like that.
大家明白了吗
Okay? So everyone understand how we kind of
我们是如何组合行为的
grouped all that stuff over there?
随着演示的进行 我们还会向这个dropitBehavior中
And we're going to add more things as this demo goes on
添加更多内容
to this kind of general dropitBehavior,
现在我们会将它们都加到另一个类中
and we're going to add them over in that other class now.
我们还会添加这里的其他行为
We're still going to add other behaviors that we add here,
并不是另一个类的内容
that really aren't part of that other thing,
但是现在我们把它们都放到一起了
but now we collected that into a nice space over there.
希望没出什么问题
So hopefully that didn't break anything,
试一下 没有
let's see, it didn't.
运行正常 很好
Okay, it's all still working, which is awesome.
现在我想做的是
Okay, so now what I want to do is,
如果像这样填满一行
when I get a full row like that,
就炸掉这一行
I want it to blow up, okay?
我不会用动力动画者来实现这个效果
And I'm going to do the blow up not using a dynamic animator.
我要用UIView动画来实现
Okay? I'm going to do that with that UIView animation business.
因为我想演示一下 这二者可以混合使用
Because I want to show you how you can mix the two together
运行正常
and they'll work fine, okay?
我们来做一下
So let's do that.
我们要怎么做呢
So how are we going to do that?
一个问题是 什么时候
Well, one question is when can I start thinking
可以开始考虑执行其他动画
about doing other animation
现在动力动画者正在运行
when I've got this dynamic animator going off
掌管一切动画
and doing all these things
弹跳 碰撞等等
bouncing and colliding and all this stuff.
答案是 可以找到
The answer is you can find out
动画者处于静止状态的时刻
when an animator reaches quiescent state,
没有弹跳 一切动画都完成了
when nothing is bouncing, everything is resolved.
一切安静下来的时候
Okay? When everything is quiet. Okay?
方法是使用动画者的委托属性
And you do that using a delegate for the animator.
如果我转到动画者
So if I go to animator here,
它有一个属性叫做delegate委托
there is a property on animator called delegate.
delegate可以发现
And the delegate is an object that's going to find out
动画者何时停止 何时再次开始
when the animator stops and when it starts up again.
我要将它设为self
And I'm going to set that to be self.
这样做之后
Now when I do that,
编译器会在这里发出一个警告
I'm going to get a warning from the compiler here.
为什么会这样
Why is that?
警告说 你将self
It says "You are assigning self,"
也就是dropit视图控制器
which is a dropit view controller,
赋值给了
"To something that's supposed
一个id类型UIDynamicAnimatorDelegate
to be an ID UIDynamicAnimatorDelegate",
换句话说
in other words, you're supposed
你应该实现这个动画者委托
to be implementing this UI animator delegate.
所以我们要在上面这里说
So we have to go up here and say
我们实现了这个UIDynamicAnimatorDelegate
that we implement this UIDynamicAnimatorDelegate.
这是我们刚才讲过的协议
This is what we're talking about, protocols
表示我们保证做什么
saying that we promised to do something.
现在没有警告了
Okay? Now, I'm not getting any more warnings,
说明这里没有必须实现的方法
so there must not be any required methods in this,
肯定都是可选的
they must all be optional.
实际上 它们确实是可选的
And in fact they are all optional,
有两个方法
and there's only two of them,
我需要的那个叫做dynamicAnimatorDidPause
and the one I want is called dynamicAnimatorDidPause,
可以看到 有两个动力动画者委托方法
you can see there's the two dynamic animator delegate methods,
dynamicAnimatorDidPause和dynamicAnimatorWillResume
dynamicAnimatorDidPause and dynamicAnimatorWillResume.
分别告诉你动画者什么时候停止
Okay, so that's telling you when it reaches a settle state
什么时候又出现变化 增加了行为或动力项
and when something changed, a behavior or an item got added,
这时动画者又重新开始
and now it's going back active again.
在这个例子中 我们想要知道它何时暂停
Okay? So in this case, we want to know the pause.
当出现暂停时
Okay? When the pause happens,
我会检查最底下一行是否被填满
I'm gonna look at that bottom row and see if it's complete.
实际上 我要检查所有行
Actually I'm going to look at all the rows
看是否有哪行被填满
and see if any of them are complete.
如果填满一行 就炸掉这行
Okay? And if they are, I'm gonna blast them out of there.
方法是调用一个方法
So I'm gonna do that by calling a method
叫做removeCompletedRows
called removeCompletedRows,
我提前做好了 节省点时间
and I have a little snippet for that to speed us up here.
就是这个方法
Okay. Here it is right here.
我没有全加进来
Okay? I didn't put it all in here.
这里写成了removeCompletedRow
Actually removeCompletedRow, I call it,
应该是removeCompletedRows
but really should be rows.
它是如何工作的呢
And so how does this work?
你们可以先听我的
Well, you can take my word for it
课下再仔细看
that this little snippet of code,
这段代码
and you can go look at it later,
基本上是填充了这个可变数组dropsToRemove
it basically just fills this mutable array, dropsToRemove
填充的是完整的一行中掉落的方块
with all the drops that are in a completed row,
即便有多行
even if there's multiple rows, okay?
用的是这个方法hitTest
It does this using this method hitTest.
我先检测全部对象
I'm actually looking at all these things
看是否有视图 如果有就抓住
and seeing if there's a view there, and if it is, I'm okay.
如果得到一整行
And if I get all the way across a row I'm like, okay,
就要把这一整行都保存下来
I've got a whole row and I'll keep them all.
这就是要移除的方块
So that's what drops to remove.
这段代码会用这些信息
This code right here is going to fill in
填写dropsToRemove数组
dropsToRemove with all the things.
现在我们有了这个数组
Okay, so now we have an array
里面是我们想要移除的方块
of the drops that we want to remove.
接下来是我们要学习的内容
Now, let's talk about what we're trying to learn here,
也就是动画 要怎样移除它们呢
which is animation, how do I remove them?
这里我要做的
And what I'm going to do, to do that,
分为两步
it's kind of a two-part deal here,
首先判断是否有要移除的方块
the first thing I'm gonna say if I have any drops to remove,
如果有 就移除全部方块
okay, then I am going to remove all of the drops
我要将视图从动画者中移除
that I'm gonna be taking out of this view from the animator,
从动力动画者中移除
from the dynamic animator,
因为我不希望动力动画者阻挡我的操作
because I don't want the dynamic animator fighting me.
我要用UIView动画移除它们
Okay? I'm gonna remove these things using UIView animation,
我不希望动画者把它们拉回去
I don't want it trying to pull them back
或者重力拉动它
or the gravity pulling on it,
我要移除它们
so I'm going to take them out,
非常简单
and I'm going to do that very simply
self.dropitBehavior removeItem:drop
by just saying self dot dropitBehavior, removeItem, drop.
遍历dropsToRemove
Okay? So I'm going through all the drops to remove,
将它们逐个从dropitBehavior中移除
and I'm removing them from my dropitBehavior.
现在它们不在任何行为中
Now they're not in any behavior,
就不会受到动画者的影响
so they're not going to be affected by the animator.
现在... 就是这样了
Okay? Now, I'm going to-- so that's that.
现在我要添加动画将它们炸掉
Now I'm going to animate the blowing them up.
方法是
Okay? And let me do that
animateRemovingDrops dropsToRemove
with animateRemovingDrops, dropsToRemove.
这是一个新方法
Okay? So this is a new method
放到这里 写在一起
that we're going to write together here,
animateRemovingDrops
animateRemovingDrops,
参数是数组dropsToRemove
it takes an array of drops to remove,
要怎么做呢
okay, how are we going to do this?
UIView animateWithDuration
Well, I'm just going to do UIView, animateWithDuration.
它有好几个版本
Okay? So I want-- there's a few versions of this,
有些有delay 有些没有
some of them have delay, some don't have delay,
我想要哪个呢
so I want the one-- which one do I want?
只要completion就够了 就是这个
I think I want the one with just completion, so that's this one.
我需要的是这个
Okay? So I want this one right here.
要多长时间呢
How long is this going to take?
我要用一秒钟炸掉它们
I'm going to take about a second to blow those things up.
这最好是一个常量
This probably wants to be a constant,
你可以调整数值以达到最好效果
and you want to tweak it to look good, right?
如果消除得太慢 看起来会很可笑
If it blows up too slowly it looks ridiculous,
如果太快 用户会看不清楚
if it blows up too fast, people can't tell
所以我们设为一秒钟
that it did it, so we'll do that.
然后是animations 就是一个block
And then here's the animations, which is just a block,
然后是completion
and here's the completion,
我不会在completion中做任何操作
which I'm not going to do anything on completion
实际上 我还是做点什么吧
actually I am going to do something on completion,
我们加些内容 演示一下
let's do something on completion just to show here.
加一个finished
So finished, okay?
就是这样
And that's it.
这就是animateWithDuration
So that's this entire animateWithDuration,
我们只要加上这两个block就行了
all we need to do is fill in these two blocks, right?
先来做这个block
So let's do this block first.
这个animations
This is the animations.
这里是实际移动操作
This is the actual moving.
我只要将这些方块移走
So all I need to do here is move these things out of the way.
我要让它们炸飞
So I'm going to have them kind of explode up
从视图顶部出去
and off the top of my view.
所以我要将它们移动到我的视图上面
So I'm going to move each one to a random location
外部的某个随机位置
somewhere off screen above my view, okay,
让它们从上面出去
kind of just out there somewhere.
怎么做呢
And so how am I going to do that,
for (UIView *drop in dropsToRemove)
by saying for, UIView drop in dropsToRemove,
随机选取一个x轴坐标
I'm gonna have the x be some random location
范围是从向左宽度大小的两倍
that is between two times my width to the left
到向右宽度大小的两倍
to two times above my width.
像一个漏斗
So it's gonna be kind of going out like this in a funnel.
x的范围是从向左两倍宽度
Okay? So the x has to be from two times my width to the left
到向右两倍宽度
to two times my width to the right,
这里也就是
so I'm going to make that be
self.gameView.bounds.size.width*5
self dot gameView dot bounds dot size dot width times five,
这样可以得到随机x轴点
okay, so that's going to get me there,
减去self.gameView.bounds.size.width*2
minus self dot gameView dot bounds dot size dot width times two.
把这段代码移到前面来
Okay. And actually I'm going to move this all back here
看得更清楚
so we can see it better,
这个也移到前面来
move this back too.
增大点空间
Okay. So let's do that, okay,
可以看到 我将五倍宽度
so you see I'm just going five wide
转变为了两倍
and I'm shifting it over two.
在上面创建它
So I'm just creating this thing above.
y轴坐标就简单了
And then the y, I'm going to make y easy,
让它等于
I'm just going to have it
self.gameView.bounds.size.height
be self dot gameView dot bounds dot size dot height,
移动方块的时候 让y轴坐标为负
and then when I move it there, I'm going to make it negative,
所以我要让drop.center等于
so I'm gonna say drop dot center equals
CGPoint(x, -y)
CGPoint x comma minus y. Alright?
在这个duration block中 如果我修改了center
So inside this duration block, if I change the center,
它是神奇的触发点之一
it's one of the magic things.
它就会运行动画
This will get animated.
center frame alpha和transform
Okay? Center, and frame, and alpha, and transform,
都能够触发自动动画
those are all the magic things that automatically will animate,
我打错了什么吗
and what did I type wrong here?
CGPointMake 对
Oh CGPointMake, yeah.
忘了Make 好样的
Make. Good job.
就是这样
Okay, so that's it.
现在方块们就会炸飞了
So now they're all going to blow up.
completion中做什么呢
What am I going to do on completion?
当它们成功炸飞之后
Well, after they blow up, if they successfully blow up,
我就要将它们从父视图中移除
I'm going to remove them all from the super view, right?
因为我不需要它们了
Because I don't want them anymore,
我炸掉了它们 它们没有了
I just blew them up, they're gone.
有什么好办法来实现呢
So what's a cool way to do that?
看这个
Watch this.
dropsToRemove makeObjectsPerformSelector:
Let's go dropsToRemove, makeObjectsPerformSelector,
@selector(removeRromSuperview)
at sign selector, removeRromSuperview.
我说了 这类方法
Okay, I told you that methods like this
会很好用 确实很好用
would come in familiar, come in handy, and they are,
这比用for-in循环好多了
it's better than having to do for, in, you know, all that stuff.
这要用这个方法
Boom, just do this,
它就会向所有目标视图发送removeFromSuperview
it's gonna send removeFromSuperview to all of them.
明白吗
Okay? Make sense?
我们来看看是否运行正常
Alright, let's see if this works.
我们加一些方块
Alright, so let's add some of these guys
等它凑满一行 还差一个
until we get a whole row, almost there, almost there.
快出来 来了
Oh, come on, oh, there it is!
这里要注意两件事
Okay, now, two things there.
炸飞动画执行了
Notice that we got the animation of the thing happening,
其他方块怎样了
but what happened to all the other blocks?
它们向下移了
They moved down, because they're all still
因为它们依旧受动画者的影响
under the influence of the animator.
重力依旧作用于它们
Gravity is still pulling on them,
碰撞依旧起作用
the collider is still working.
如果我再增加一些方块
So if I put a whole bunch of things in here, okay,
它们有点倾斜了 再看一遍
and also okay they're kind of tilting, watch this again.
糟糕
Oop...
没错
Yeah, I did.
hitTest确实不太靠谱
I did get unlucky with the hitTest there,
再重新运行一下吧
here let me show you a different way.
用hitTest来实现这个效果
The hitTest is kind of a questionable way
不是一个可靠的方法
to do that, by the way.
我来演示一下
But, here, let's show you.
再重新看一遍
I'll just show you this again.
而且 我应该让它们不这样倾斜
Also, I should make it so that they're not tilting like that.
我们下次再做
We'll do that next time.
又不出来吗 来了
But...wow, I'm getting-- There we go.
喂 怎么回事
Okay. Hello.
动一下 动一下
Knock, knock, knock.
我不知道为什么不行
Well, I don't know why it's not working now,
但好歹你们刚才看到了 该下课了
but anyway you got to see it work and time's up,
我们会再看一下
but we'll look at that,
后面会再看一下
we'll look at that later
看看问题出在哪
and try and find out what our problem was.
但是 这里主要要注意 我们让方块飞走了
But anyway, the main thing there to notice, we did the fly away,
但是动画者依旧作用于其他对象
but we also had the animator still working on the other things,
要知道这一点很重要
and that's important to know,
这二者可以这样互相作用
that the two things can interact like that.
如果你将某些元素移走
If you move things out of the way,
动画者会重新开始
the animator is going to go back to life
继续拉动物体
and start pulling down on things, okay?
下次我们会继续完成这个动画
So next time, we'll continue to do the animation,
我们不会再让它这么摇晃了
we'll make it so it's not so rickety, okay,
避免出现
so we don't have this problem
底部无法对齐的问题
where the bottom load doesn't line up,
我们还会增加一个吸附行为
and we'll also do an attachment,
吸附到某个元素上
where we attach to something and, you know,
用吸附行为
have it swing from an attachment,
让它挂到某个吸附对象上
with a little attachment behavior.
好了 下次见
Alright, we'll see you next time.
更多内容 请访问斯坦福网站
For more, please visit us at Stanford.edu.